<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Advice to an only child, or, Excellent council to all young persons containing, the summ and substance of experimental and practical divinity / written by an eminent and judicious divine, for the private use of an only child, now made publick for the benefit of all.</title>
            <author>Heywood, Oliver, 1629-1702.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 192 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 96 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43569</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1758</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18548</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12560217</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12560217</idno>
            <idno type="VID">63142</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43569)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 63142)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 319:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Advice to an only child, or, Excellent council to all young persons containing, the summ and substance of experimental and practical divinity / written by an eminent and judicious divine, for the private use of an only child, now made publick for the benefit of all.</title>
                  <author>Heywood, Oliver, 1629-1702.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 173 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Parkhurst ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to the author of the prefatory epistle (signed O.H.), Oliver Heywood. Cf. BM; Wing; Sloane, W. Children's books in England and America, no. 212.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Conduct of life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian education of children.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:63142:1"/>
            <p>ADVICE To an Only CHILD: OR, <hi>Excellent Council</hi> TO ALL Young Perſons.</p>
            <p>Containing, The Summ and Subſtance of Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental and Practical Divinity.</p>
            <p>WRITTEN By an Eminent and Judicious Divine, for the Private Uſe of an only Child, now made Publick for the Benefit of all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt,</hi> at the <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> and <hi>Three Crowns,</hi> at the lower end of <hi>Cheap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide,</hi> near <hi>Mercers</hi> Chapel. 1693.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:63142:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:63142:2"/>
            <head>THE Epiſtle to the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THIS precious Pearl of ſeaſonable Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice providentially put firſt into my Hand, and now into thine, is of great worth, and the rate thereof is inhanced both from the worthineſs of the Authour, and the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of the ſubject matter, the manner of handling it, and the great End and Deſign of it: The Authour was a Maſter in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> a Star of the firſt Magnitude, firſt placed in an high elevation to influence Candidates for the Miniſtry in the Academical Orb, thence tranſlated by the Miniſterial Functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on into an Eccleſiaſtical Station, where he was a burning and ſhining light, till Eclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with the reſt of his ejected Brethren, but moved very regularly and profitably in a nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rower and obſcurer Sphear, till at laſt he diſappeared to us, but ſhines bright in the Firmament of Glory: his exquiſite pains, of the Stone, with his invincible Patience and Magnanimity would make a volume: his perſonal excellencies, as a Schollar, as a
<pb facs="tcp:63142:3"/>
Miniſter, as a Chriſtian, were beyond the vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar rate: and 'tis pity the World is bleſſed with no more of his learned labours, poliſhed with his own hand, and ſquared by this Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Builder for adorning the Houſe of God: but his Modeſty concealed ſomething of what our zeal for publick good hath here pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to the Reader in its naked dreſs as writ by his own Hand.</p>
            <p>As for the Matter, it is thoſe <hi>[Magna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia Dei,]</hi> the Doctrine according to Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs the weighty things of Law and Goſpel, Covenanting with God, the Life of Faith, of Holineſs, as in Gods preſence, acting of love to God, Chriſt, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Obedience, circumſpect walking, dying daily, Repentance, delighting in God, and his Ways, thankfulneſs, Prayer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> you may find in this Treatiſe an excellent Encyclopoedia or <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Scheme of Practical Divinity: coucht in a few words, in a plain method laid before the Eyes of the intelligent Reader.</p>
            <p>The manner of managing this uſeful tractate is pleaſant and taking, and adds a peculiar Accent and Emphaſis to it, ſuch a ſmooth ſtile, ſuch pat and proper ſimilitudes, and delightful alluſions, that it will chain the Readers Eye to proceed in reading, and may perhaps charm his affections to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace
<pb facs="tcp:63142:3"/>
the contents thereof:<note place="margin">Prov. 25 11.</note> It is as Apples of Gold in Pictures of Silver, <hi>i. e.</hi> Golden Apples appearing through Net-work of Silver, or Pourtrayed on Silver Tables, very delightful, and grateful to the Eye, ſo may theſe words <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> on the Wheel. <hi>v.</hi> 12.</note> fitly ſpoken be to Youth: and (as in the next verſe) as an Earing of Gold, and Ornament of fine Gold, ſo may this wiſe Reprover be upon an obedient Ear: happy is the Teacher that mixeth pleaſant and profitable.</p>
            <p>The Deſign, (I am ſure) is high and noble, to plant Grace in young Perſons, and to breed and feed a nurſery of Plants of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nown, to ſtock the Church and World with a ſpringing up generation, in the room of old trees tranſplanted into a better ſoil; that may fill up vacancies and do God ſervice in after-times: Amongſt the reſt of <hi>Solomons</hi> ſumptuous preparations of coſtly Ornaments for his pleaſures, that was not the leaſt which he mentions, <hi>Eccleſ. 2.6.</hi> I made me pools of Water, to water therewith the Wood that bringeth forth Trees: this was an Artificial mean of nouriſhing Fruit-trees, in want of natural diſtillings of Rain from the Clouds, which ſometimes was rare and ſcant: and 'tis worth obſerving, that the
<pb facs="tcp:63142:4"/>
word rendered [Pools] is the ſame with Bleſſing in Hebrew either becauſe in thoſe hot Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys they were eſteemed great bleſſings,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Piſcina à <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> benedicit.</note> or becauſe they were filled with Rain which is the great Bleſſing of God. Such Pools, as this ſmall Treatiſe, are ſignal Bleſſings in themſelves, may they be alſo ſeconded with the Heavenly Dew of Divine Benediction, what a Wood or For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of Fruit-bearing Trees may we ſee flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing in the Orchard of Gods Church? It's true Men may do ſomething, yet not all. The beſt humane cultivating bows the Trees but to an outward compliance, Divine Grace only plants them in Chriſt, and plants Grace in their Hearts.<note place="margin">2 Kin. 12.2. 2 Chron. 24.1<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 22.</note> The Pupil <hi>Joaſh</hi> was hopeful whileſt his Reverend Tutour <hi>Jehojada</hi> inſtructed [or beſprinkled] him, but after his Death diſcovered the rottenneſs of his hypocritical Heart. God will demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate a vaſt difference, betwixt the Effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient cauſe and ſubordinate means, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſome miſcarry under Religious Educati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: but ſome prove well, to incourage Parents and Masters in their duty: Divine Benediction with paternal instruction hath done great things. Let <hi>Abraham</hi> command his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,
<pb facs="tcp:63142:4"/>
God undertakes they ſhall keep the way of the Lord:<note place="margin">Gen. 18, 19.</note> The Rain alſo filleth the Pools ſaith the <hi>Pſalmiſt, Pſal. 84</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Benedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionibus amicietur Doctor, or Benedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionem dabit Legiſlator,</hi> the Eternal Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty will make their Pools of Water great Bleſſings to Men.</p>
            <p>Did Parents Conſcientiouſly in ſtru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Children, they would in Gods time diſcern the Bleſſed effects thereof: Reverend Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> thinks, Religious Education would be ſo Bleſſed by God for Converſion, that publick Miniſtry would be chiefly uſeful for Edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Tis true, Grace comes not by Succeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yet oft in Succeſſion; the Covenant is with the Godly and their Seed; and ſurely it's not an inſignificant Cypher: As God delights to run along the line of Goſpel Covenant, ſo he uſually bleſſeth his own Inſtitutions with Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel Grace: Let Parents do Duty, and leave their iſſue to God: Our Children have Souls as well as Bodies, both muſt be cared for, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture obligeth unto nurture, Grace regulates it, God alone makes it efficacious,<note place="margin">Job 11, 12.</note> Corrupt Nature leaves Children not a whit better, than a wild Aſſes Colt, an habit of Sinning makes them a wild Aſs,
<pb facs="tcp:63142:5"/>
uſed to the Wilderneſs that ſnuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feth up the wind at her pleaſure,<note place="margin">Jer. 2.24.</note> in her occaſion who can turn her away? Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation muſt be as guide and bridle, to teach and tame theſe frolick Youths: But alas, moſt Parents caſt the Reins in Childrens Necks, and leave them to their wanton ways, till at laſt they get the Bits between the Teeth, and kick off the Rider, and ramble in forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den paths, till they are impounded in a Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or an Halter here, and in the Dungeon of Hell hereafter: <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, The Rod and Reproof give Wiſdom,<note place="margin">Prov 29.15.</note> but a Child left to himſelf, bringeth his Mother to ſhame: Is not Crying here, bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than Roaring in Eternal Torments? Even Heathen <hi>Seneca</hi> could ſay, <hi>[Diſciplina ſevera firmat ingenia, &amp; apta reddit mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis conatibus]</hi> is it not pitty ſuch ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous youths ſhould be loſt, for want of Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and Correction? Let Parents and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours Tremble, leſt the Blood of Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons Souls ſhould lye at their Door, and both be Tormented for wilful neglects: Even Heathens had great care of Childrens Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, it was actionable in the Law-Courts among the <hi>Romans</hi> to neglect this, yea, if the Son was Debauched, the Father was ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb facs="tcp:63142:5"/>
ſince it was ſuppoſed the Sons Miſcarri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age was through the Fathers Default: But that might be a miſtake: Yet God that ſees all things, and whoſe Judgment is always according to truth, will Commence a Suit againſt, and Condemn the careleſs Parent: Lord, when will Parents have as much care of their Childrens Souls as Bodies? Yea, expreſs as much tenderneſs to a Child, as to a Beaſt! You labour hard to provide for them Food and Rayment, to put them into callings, that they may live like Men in the World and are their Souls of no Worth? Is there not another World worth thinking of, looking after? Have you not many helps the Bible, Catechiſmes, good Books, Miniſters to Move, Admoniſh and inſtruct you in train<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up your Children? Do you not promiſe to do this for them at their Baptiſm? Could you be content to ſee a Maſtiff Dog drag away your Child, pull out his Entrals, &amp; feed upon him, and not ſtir a foot, ſpeak a word to reſcue him? O miſerable parents! O Cruel Tygers! Worſe than Sea monſters,<note place="margin">Lam. 4<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> that draw out the Breaſts, they give ſuck to their young ones, and have not you a word to ſpeak, not a breath to breathe in Prayer, not a Hand to reach out to them, to pluck
<pb facs="tcp:63142:6"/>
them from this <hi>Gerberus,</hi> this Dog of Hell? Oh where's Grace, yea, where is Nature! The Lord pitty theſe mercileſs Parents: For ſhame learn your Duty, and do it, and take this Book for an help.</p>
            <p>And you that are Children, if Parents neglected their Duty, do not you neglect God and your Souls: They lookt no further than your Preferment in the World; but do you look after an Everlaſting Happineſs in the other World: Some commended <hi>Patricius, Auguſtines</hi> Father, for Educating his Son a Scholar, who became ſo Famous a Father in the Church; Alas ſaid he, my Father ſought only to make me a Rhetorician, not a Chriſtian, for he was an Heathen: But whatever your Parents Trained you up for, Law or Phyſick, or a Trade, Study Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity: If thy Parents were Carnal, Lament it, Act Faith in Chriſt, to get Guilt taken off thy Fathers Houſe, and double thy Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence for thy own Soul, and for thy Seed: If thy Parents were godly, devoted thee to God, ſet thee a good Example, inſtructed, prayed for thee: O make much of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Parents, plead it, embrace it, and ſee thy Heart and Life be Squared by it: Elſe thy Priviledges will be a Teſtimony
<pb facs="tcp:63142:6"/>
againſt thee another Day: <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſhop of Millain</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that in the primitive <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> or white Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> was put upon the party Baptized; and the Miniſter <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, take this white and immaculate Veſtment, and ſee thou king it forth without Spot at the Judgment Seat of Chriſt: Withal, he tells of one <hi>Elpidophorus</hi> being Baptized, afterwards proving a prophane Wretch, the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter produced this Garment, ſaying, This Linnen ſhall <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> thee at Chriſts coming, which is witneſs of thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>tacy: You young people, make a great account, that you were made Chriſtians in Baptiſm, and indeed it ſtands in good ſtead in your Infant-State, by vertue of your Parents Covenant, but being grown up, you ſtand upon your own Legs, and muſt perſonally renew your Baptiſmal Covenant, or expect no benefit by it: Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm will not ſave you, without the Anſwer of a good Conſcience:<note place="margin">1 Pet. 3.21. Tit. 3.<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> The lover of Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration will not avail to Adult Perſons, without the renewing of the Holy Ghoſt: You muſt be born again of water, and of the Spirit, or you cannot enter into the Kingdom of God:<note place="margin">Joh. 3.5.</note> To which <hi>Auſtin</hi> Subſcribes, ſaying <hi>[Nihil profuit Simoni Mago viſibilis Baptiſmus cui Sanctificatio inviſibilis deſit]</hi> you know <hi>Simon Magus</hi> was in the Gall of Bitterneſs, and Bond of Iniquity,<note place="margin">Act. 8.13.22.</note> though he was Baptized: You are to thank God for External Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges, and Religious Education, they are Signal Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, not common to all; <hi>Bucholzer</hi> thankt God that he was Bred up under <hi>Melancthon,</hi> Mr. <hi>Whately</hi> under Mr. <hi>Dod,</hi> yea, a <hi>Plato,</hi> that he was Pupil to <hi>Socrates:</hi> But reſt not here, be not ſatisfied except the unfeigned faith dwell in thee,<note place="margin">2 Tim 1.5.</note> alſo that was in thy pious Aunceſtors: Mind their Godly Examples, and do not contradict them: A King of Poland was wont to carry the Picture of his Renowned Father in a <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ate of God about his Neck, when he went about any notable Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploit, kiſſing it, he ſaid, God grant I may <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> nothing Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſely
<pb facs="tcp:63142:7"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of ſo <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> you <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Heb. 6.12.</note> who through Faith and patience, do now inherit the promiſes, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to be <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>piſh, imitators of their outward Acts, but ſee you have the ſame Spirit of Faith, Love, fear of God, Repentance, and n<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>w Obedience: Think you hear your Dying Parents charging you, (as Mr. Bol<gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> did his Children) that <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of you dare to meet them at the great Day, without a Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Garment: To this <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> attend daily at a <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Miniſtry, examine your Conſciences by the Word of God, pray much in Secret, be Humble and D<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cible, Diſdain not to learn Catechiſms, watch againſt Occaſions of Sin got into, and improve Chriſtian Society, keep Conſcience void of Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence towards God and Man: Read, Meditate on, labour to and ſtand and practice Scripture Truths and Rules: Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to do all the good you can, and be uſeful in your Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration.</p>
            <p>But I ſhall detain you no longre in the Porch, I humbly deſire you to Read and Study this enſuing Treatiſe, which though ſhort, is yet Pithy, Accurate, and Sententi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and will like a Clew, lead thee through the Laby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinths and Meanders of the World: Omit the reading of it, and thou are a loſer, read it ſlightly, and thou gaineſt no good, contradict it at thy peril, theſe Sheets will riſe up in Judgment againſt thee another Day: My earneſt Prayer ſhall follow this and other Soul-helps, that the God of all Grace would ſtamp his own Bleſſed Image on the Souls of the Riſing Generation, awake their Conſciences, inlighten their Minds, renew their Natures, ſubdue their Wills, raiſe their Affections to Heavenly Objects, that they may fill up our vacancies when our Heads are laid in the Silent Duſt; and may ſee better Ways, and have better Heads, to improve all Occurrences to better purpoſe, than we that are now going off the Stage: And thus, good Reader, I take leave, wiſhing thee much content and Advantage in peruſing this ſweet Poſy of Spiritual Flowers, gathered out of the Scripture Garden: As</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>That Soul-Friend, and Servant in Chriſt, O. H.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:63142:7"/>
            <head>A PARENTS ADVICE to his CHILD, How to Live well.</head>
            <div type="introduction">
               <head>The Introduction.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Daughter,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>MY hearts deſire and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to God for you is, that you might be ſaved, and thereupon I do Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel in Birth for you, till Chriſt be form'd in you: Wherefore (as <hi>Paul</hi>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:63142:8"/>
wrote to <hi>Philemon</hi>) though I might be bold in Chriſt to enjoyn you, yet for Loves ſake, I rather beſeech you, being ſuch a one as your Father the Aged, and a Servant of Jeſus Chriſt. I beſeech you (not, as he for an <hi>One Simus</hi>) but for your ſelf, whom I have begotten, and O that I could ſay, had begotten again, though it were in my bonds! and ſo could in this reſpect further ſay in the words of that Apoſtle there, <hi>Thou oweſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me even thine own ſelf;</hi> yea Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, let me have joy of you in the Lord, refreſh my Bowels in the Lord, which you will do, if I may have confidence in your Obedience, that you will do what I ſay, which I may the more expect from you, ſith the Counſel I here give you, is no other than what I have received from mine, and your Heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: and therefore I may ſay confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently of it, what was ſaid of <hi>Ahito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phels,</hi> that it is, as if one had inquired of the Oracles of God, for it is ſuch, as I had from the Word of God,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:63142:8"/>
which is called the Oracles of God. And though I be your Father, yet I could willingly go down upon my knees to you, begging of you for your Souls ſake, that you would em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace it, which if you do, then bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed are you among Women: for God will guide you with his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, and afterwards receive you to Glory. But if you refuſe it, you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject the Counſel of God againſt your ſelf, and this paper will riſe up in Judgement againſt you.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:63142:9"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Of Covenanting with God in Chriſt.</head>
               <p n="1">1. IN the firſt place I do beſeech you in the Bowels of a tender Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and as you will anſwer the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyal of ſo reaſonable a requeſt at the Tribunal of God, before the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Judge of Men and Angels, that you would ſeriouſly, intirely, and unreſervedly make an oblation of your ſelf in Covenant, a ſolemn De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of all your faculties, both of Soul and Body, to God the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, as your only God, Redeemer and Sanctifier, bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding your ſelf thereby to forſake that malicious Trinity, the World, the Fleſh &amp; the Devil. Reſign up and make over your ſelf wholly and intirely to the Lord, to the obedience of him. Subſcribe to all his Laws, bid an ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter defiance to all his enemies; out-brave all oppoſition, and Triumph over all in the Lord.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:63142:9"/>2. Here let me remind you, that this is that which I ſolemnly Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanted in your behalf, at your Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, and you being come to Age, are bound to perform, and make good, which if you ſhould not do, but recede from that engagement, I ſhould tremble to think, how ſad your caſe would be. Had you died in your Childhood as my other Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren did, then you had reaped the benefit of the Covenant, according to the faith of your own Parents; but now you muſt ſtand or fall by your own faith, &amp; ſincere conſent thereunto, as the Child while an Infant is carried in the Mothers or Nurſes Arms, but when grown up, muſt ſtand upon its own legs.</p>
               <p n="3">3. I intreat you therefore, I warn you, as a Father, do that firſt which muſt needs be done, and is of great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Importance, the moſt momen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous concern, be ſure that your Soul be ſafe, and ſecure, as to its everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting condition; Act <hi>Maries</hi> part, by looking after the one thing neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: and therefore get to be in Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:63142:10"/>
with God in Chriſt by your hearty conſent thereunto: for this is the true condition, and certain evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of your intereſt in the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, your Title to all the rich Lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies thereof, as namely to God the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, as your Reconciled God and Father, Redeemer and Sanctifier, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently to all the ſaving Bleſſings and Priviledges, both of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Grace and Glory, which are all couched therein. In the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, God the Father conſents, or enters into Bond, in the ſight and preſence of Angels and glorified Souls, to be our God, Jeſus Chriſt to be our Saviour, and the Holy Ghoſt to be our Sanctifier, (in which compen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious and immenſe grant, all things are comprized that you can ask or think.) If you then reciprocally conſent, and engage your ſelf to take God the Father to be your only God, the Son to be your Saviour, to ſave you from Sin, as well as from Hell, and the Holy Ghoſt to be your Sanctifier, to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:63142:10"/>
make you by degrees perfectly holy then the Covenant is complete, your Intereſt therein ſecure, and your Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle good to all the rich Bleſſings laid up in this Ark of the Covenant, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, your conſent be ſuch as doth bloſſom forth into the duties which you conſent unto, and produce a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing of the World, the Fleſh, and the Devil, which is involved and enwrapped therein: for you do not take God to be your God, if you take him only to receive his pay, and not to fight under his Banner, againſt thoſe his malicious enemies. You do not take him to be your God, unleſs you take him to be your <hi>All,</hi> and be ready to renounce and forſake all for him, and prefer him in your love and eſteem, above all things, ſo as to let him turn the ballance, and his intereſt to weigh down the Scales a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all the World; and unleſs you ſet him alone in the Throne, &amp; in the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Chariot, to ride Triumphantly in the Soul over all enemies. How readily doth the Wiſe Merchant in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:63142:11"/>
the Goſpel ſell all for the Pearl, that is more precious than Rocks of Rubies and Mountains of Diamonds? Thus it will be with you, if your Covenant conſent be not weak and languid, but ſtrong and well fixed. Indeed a ſmall rub may turn aſide a Bowl, that hath but a weak Byaſs, but if it hath a ſtrong one it will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover, and get into its way again. See then that your conſent be ſo ſtrong and full, as may paſs you under the bond of the Covenant, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry you over to God and Chriſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all oppoſition. But think it not enough that this Covenant be once made, it muſt be often renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and followed with an anſwerable practice.</p>
               <p n="4">4. This is my firſt and grand ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, yea the very Abridgment and Summ of all your duty, this entring in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, &amp; keeping faithfully the Baptiſmal Covenant is your very Chriſtianity &amp; real Godlineſs; it's your building upon a Rock, your doing the one thing neceſſary, and your giving to God
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:63142:11"/>
the things that are Gods. It's a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying of your ſelf, taking up the Croſs, and following the Lord Jeſus; it's a delivering of your ſelf over to the Lord Jeſus, to be Married to him, a taking him as your Husband, to Love, Honour, and Obey him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all; And to this Match you have my full and free conſent, yea my daily prayers for it. O that as a ſpokes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man for Chriſt, I could tell how to woe for him, and uſe ſuch Rhetorick that I might prevail, look upon the height of his Stature, like <hi>Saul</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the People there is none like him: View him in all his excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, he is white and ruddy, the Chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt among ten thouſand, fairer than all the Children of Men, and your ſelf will be complete in him. Know for your encouragement, that you ſhall have the richeſt Dowry in all the World: for all that Chriſt and Heaven is worth ſhall be yours, the Wife being intereſted in all her Husbands Goods; he will advance you to a Kingdom, and Feoffe you
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:63142:12"/>
in all the riches of it. Say then, Lord, if I had Ten Thouſand ſelves, I would give them all up to thee, who haſt ſhewed to me ſuch won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Love, as to offer to give up thy ſelf to me. I will take thee with all my heart, I give my free and hearty conſent, let the Match be made, and aſſure your ſelf then, that it ſhall be made up, the Spirit of Chriſt will be aſſiſtant to Faith in Tying the Marriage knot.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Of Living the Life of Faith.</head>
               <p n="1">1. LIve the Life of Faith in a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual dependence upon God in Chriſt, for all things neceſſary, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially for the Soul. Six hundred and Thirteen precepts have been obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be in the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> by ſome of the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Doctors, who had the leiſure to number them, and they tell us that they are all wrapt up by the Prophet <hi>Habakkuk</hi> in that one
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:63142:12"/>
ſhort ſentence; <hi>The juſt ſhall live by Faith.</hi> Sure it is a very pregnant and comprehenſive duty, for Faith is an Obediential Affiance, and ſo is a pair of Compaſſes, one foot whereof, <hi>viz.</hi> Affiance, being pitch'd upon the Center, which is God, the other goes round in a perfect Circle of all holy Duties. Faith ſurveys the whole Land of promiſe, ſearches it out throughly, ſpies out all the rich Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures that lye in the golden mines of the promiſes, and finds ſuitable provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in every caſe, both for Soul and for Body, which in it can fetch in time of need: and ſo it hath work enough daily for a conſtant and continued employment, becauſe every moment we are under ſome ſpiritual want.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As for temporal good things, live by Faith in a holy dependency and indifferency, reſting contented with the will of God, whatſoever it be. A believer though the Bill of fare be ſhort, lives on the wiſe po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werful and gracious providence of God, not doubting but he ſhall have
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:63142:13"/>
enough to pay for his paſſage, thorugh the Sea of this World to Heaven. How many live on the Trencher of Gods Providence in their mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, who never live on that provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in a gracious dependance, or by actings of Faith in a promiſe? Do not moſt Perſons live wholly by their Friends, by their Credit and Intereſt in the World? but where is the Man or Woman that Lives by Faith?</p>
               <p n="3">3 Fetch in proviſion for your Soul daily by actings of Faith. Let Faith make out to Chriſt for new ſupplies of ſpiritual ſtrength, grace and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in all your need: Faith is our Purveyor, till we come to the Mount of God, and goes a Catering for us, till we come to that Land, that flows with Milk and Hony. God is a rich Mine of Wiſdom and Grace, which can never be digged to the bottom, and hath inexhauſtible Treaſures lock'd up in Chriſt, continually ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ready by him, only ſtays for Faith to come and fetch them. He
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:63142:13"/>
is not pleaſed to give us in a full ſupply of all at once, but crumbles out his mercies, and gives his bleſſings by retail, to teach us by Faith to live upon him daily. <hi>Manna</hi> fell every morning. God could if he had plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, have given them as much at once, as ſhould have ſerved them all the time, that they were to be in the Wilderneſs, but he would teach them by his daily gift, to depend up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Providence for it daily. Thus God is pleaſed to deliver out to his dear Children every day, a ſet allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, it may be but a Crum of hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den <hi>Manna,</hi> a taſt of his ſpecial Love, when he could fill an Omer of it if he pleaſed, it may be he reaches forth to a believer, only ſome Grapes of the Heavenly <hi>Canaan,</hi> when he could throw cluſters thereof into his Lap. He could have ſo form'd the new-born Babe in Chriſt, and have caſt it into ſuch a Mould in the New-birth, as that it ſhould have been per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in that inſtant, as <hi>Adam</hi> was in the moment of Creation; but he will have this Babe of grace to go by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:63142:14"/>
from Faith to Faith, from Strength to Strength, till it come to full perfection. The king appointed a daily Proviſion of his meat, and of the Wine which he drank to certain of the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> Dan. 1.5. Thus doth the King of Heaven, he will not give all grace at once out of his Store-houſe, nor let the Pot of hidden <hi>Manna</hi> be in our keeping; he doth not think fit we ſhould have his Royal Wine of ſpiritual Joy and Comfort in our own Cellars, to go to when we pleaſe, leſt we ſhould drink and forget our ſelves, yea and him too, leſt it ſhould fume up and make our Heads giddy, or our Blood too rank our Spirits too high &amp; proud: for it is no eaſie matter to carry the brim-full Cup of Conſolation ſteddily and equally; though the Soul have rich joy to day, yet it may have none to morrow, unleſs he pleaſe to ſend a draught of this Cordial Wine from his own Table. And why is all this, but to teach us to live by Faith and wait continually upon him for new Influences? The wiſe Father keeps
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:63142:14"/>
the ſtock in his own hands, and gives not all at once, to keep his Son in a dependence.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Of the Life of Holineſs.</head>
               <p>LIve the Life of Holineſs. This directly follows the Life of Faith: for all holineſs ſprings from Faith, and the more you live the Life of Faith, the more you will live the Life of holineſs. Now if you would live this Holy Life, you muſt do theſe five things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Get a principle of holineſs; you cannot live a Life of holineſs, unleſs there be firſt a principle of holineſs within. Can the Body ſtir or move without a principle of Life? how can there be actual holineſs in the Life, where there is not firſt habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual holineſs in the Heart?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Make holineſs the very work of your Life, or devote your ſelf to the work of holineſs: he lives a Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents life, or the life of a Scholar, who devotes himſelf to his Studies. You do then live a Holy Life,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:63142:15"/>
when you make holineſs the very buſineſs of your Life; when the Courſe and Tenor and main Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of your Life is Holineſs, when you make a Trade of it. Do you only perform Holy Duties by fits and ſtarts? do you make ſtops and pauſes? are you off and on, and act holily only occaſionally? or in ſome certain good moods, or on ſome Holy days? this is not to live a Life of Holineſs. You muſt conſtantly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy your ſelf therein, and follow af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it in the whole courſe of your Life. And therefore let me now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeak you in the words of a Holy Man, now with the Lord. <hi>Let Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs ſit in your Lips, and ſeaſon all your Speech with Grace, let it dwell in your Heart, let it be your companion in your Cloſet, let it Travel with you in your Journey, let it lye down and riſe up with you, let it cloſe your Eyes in the Evening, and call you out of your Bed in the Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Make holineſs the main deſign and end of your Life: Then indeed
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:63142:15"/>
you live the Life of Holineſs, when holineſs, which is the main deſign of Chriſtianity, is the great deſign of your Life, when the very drift, purport and intent of your Life is to live to God.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Spend all the time of your Life that you can redeem from other oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions in the duties of holineſs, while others ſteal time from holy du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties for their Worldly buſineſs and pleaſures, do you borrow all the time that you can from thoſe things, yea from your ſleep for holy duties.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Put forth your Vital Power, your Life, your Vigor and Strength in Exerciſes of Holineſs. Summon in all the powers of your ſoul, let none be wanting. Whatſoever your Heart findeth to do in the Work of Religion, do it with all your might; ply your Oars, hoiſe up your Sails, put forward with all your power and ſtrength, with might and main, in your courſe toward Heaven. By thus doing you will certainly live the Life of Holineſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:63142:16"/>It may be you may meet with ſome ſcoffs, amongſt ſome <hi>Iſhmaels,</hi> for ſuch a Holy Life; bat yet let not this diſcourage, or take you off from following the ways of holineſs and uprightneſs. What if a Lame Man ſhould laugh at your upright walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, would you therefore go lame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly? But for your better encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment I ſhall propound to you one Motive.</p>
               <p>Conſider that unleſs you live the Life of holineſs, you can never live the Life of glory: <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nleſs you be Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated and Born again, you can never enter into the Kingdom of God,</hi> John 3.3. It's only the New Creature that muſt be admitted into the New <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem.</hi> You will never be a Flower in the Paradiſe of Heaven, unleſs you firſt be Tranſplanted out of the common field of Nature into Chriſt's holy Garden. <hi>Without Holineſs no one ſhall ever ſee the Lord.</hi> Heb. 12.14. It's this that fits the very Angels for Heaven; and therefore without it how can you ever think to come
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:63142:16"/>
there? It's not the Angelical Nature, but their Holineſs, that makes them fit for Heaven, and therefore it's more excellent than the very Nature of the Angels conſidered in it ſelf: for it is the Image of God, as a bright beam of the Divine Nature, and ſo makes us capable of Heaven. My Heart therefore yearns for you, my Bowels rowl within me, out of ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der affection to your Soul, leſt you ſhould come ſhort of Holineſs, and thereby come ſhort of Heaven. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Virtues without Holineſs will never be a <hi>Jacobs</hi> Ladder to reach Heaven, how near ſoever they may come to it. O what pity is it that an Ingenuous Nature, ſhould by ſome Moral accompliſhments, come near to Heaven, and yet never come there? that <hi>Rachel</hi> ſhould dye, when it was but a little way to come to <hi>Ephrath!</hi> Be ſure therefore to add the practice and power of Godlineſs, as a full fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure to your Cyphers: For unleſs you do this, I ſhall never have hope to ſee your Face in Heaven, which is an undefiled Inheritance.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:63142:17"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Of Living as in Gods Preſence.</head>
               <p n="1">1. LIve always as in the preſence of God, and as under his jealouſie. Thus did good <hi>Elizabeth</hi> in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, of whom it is ſaid, <hi>That ſhe was Righteous before God, or in the Eyes of the Lord,</hi> (as the Vulgar Latin reads it.) <hi>Luke</hi> 1.6. It was good counſel of one of the <hi>Rabbins,</hi> that we ſhould always think, that there was an Eye that ſaw all, an Ear hearing all, and an Hand writing all. Often repeat the 1<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>9. <hi>Pſalm</hi> to your ſelf, and ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly conſider that God is in all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and not only in the place where you are, but within you, in your ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Breaſt and Boſom, viewing all your thoughts and intentions, not with a bare beholding, but with a critical Eye, and as a Judge to cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure them, to approve or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn them. Whereupon <hi>his eye-lids are ſaid to try the Children of Men,</hi> Pſal. 11.4. You cannot ſhut the Heart
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:63142:17"/>
ſo cloſe, but he hath a Key to unlock it, he draws the Curtain and ſees what is within, he ſpies out what is Cabinetted and lock'd up in the moſt ſecret Corner and private Drawer there. The bright and piercing Eye of Omniſcience ſees the very inward Conceptions before they come to the Birth, the firſt eruptions and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bullitions of a Thought or Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If you do all things, as believing that this Eye is upon you, it will have a great influence on your Life. What a holy trembling and quive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring diſpoſition would this create in you, leſt you ſhould offend ſo Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous an Eye? What a Curb and Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle would it be to reſtrain from all Sin even from ſecret Hypocriſie? What a ſharp Goad and Spur to all Uprightneſs? The Maſters Eye makes the Servant work. Do but ſerve God faithfully while he ſees you, and it is enough. I have read of one that committing a foul Sin, ſaid to himſelf, <hi>No Eye ſees me,</hi> but
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:63142:18"/>
preſently there appear'd an Eye on the Wall with this Inſcription, <hi>But this Eye ſees thee.</hi> If you did always keep within you freſh apprehenſions of God as preſent, you would not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit a diſhonourable thought of him in your Heart, nor let an evil word have paſſage through the door of your Lips.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Know for your encouragement that if you thus live, as in Gods awful Preſence, you ſhall enjoy very much his gracious Preſence here, and his Glorious Preſence hereafter to all Eternity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Of Living in Love to God and Chriſt.</head>
               <p n="1">1. LIve in love to God and Jeſus Chriſt, do all things out of a principle of Love to God your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and Jeſus Chriſt the only Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our. God muſt be loved as your ultimate end, the enjoyment of whom is the Souls everlaſting bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſs,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:63142:18"/>
and Chriſt as Mediator muſt be loved, as the only way whereby we are reconciled to God, and come to obtain that bleſſedneſs. If you live not in the love of God, how can you ever expect to live in his favour, or that he will either accept you, or your Services? for it is this Love that perfumes all our actions, and makes them a ſweet Odour unto God. Love to God is the very Life and Soul of all Natural Religion, and Love to Chriſt is the Spirit and Vital principle, that animates all E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelical Duties, which are requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the New Covenant, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no duty will be acceptible with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Look well to it, that your love to God and Chriſt be a ſingular, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perlative, tranſcendent Love, a Love that out-ballanceth all other Love whatſoever. It muſt be the higheſt degree, the very Cream, Flower and Top of your Affection. I do not mean in reſpect of the paſſionateneſs of it (for your love to Creatures
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:63142:19"/>
may be more paſſionate) but in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the high eſtimation of him, adhering to him, and readineſs to forego all for him, you muſt value the Intereſt of God in Chriſt above your own, nothing muſt have more of your heart. Chriſt muſt be above ſelf, and above every thing elſe in the heart; nothing elſe muſt be ſuffered to creep into the Bed of Love.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If there be any thing elſe that lies nearer the heart than Chriſt, the Fountain of your ſpiritual life, it will hinder your Union with him, and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in him. The leaſt Chip that falls betwixt the graft and the joynt hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders its knitting to the ſtock, and maketh the graft to die. Let no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing then lie in the joynt betwixt Chriſt and your Heart, to prevent and hinder your happy and bleſſed Union, and keep you from cloſing with him, embracing of him and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in him.</p>
               <p n="4">4. There may be in an Unrege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate Perſon a true love to God and Chriſt. I mean ſuch a true love, as is
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:63142:19"/>
not diſſembling love, but yet it fails in the degree; there's other love to ſelf that pirks above it and over-tops it, and ſo damps this affection that it never flames out to God and Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Now that you may get this ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perlative love to God and Chriſt wrought in you, you muſt take pains with your own heart, otherwiſe you will not bring it up to this high pitch. Strike the flint hard to bring out Fire, and pray to Chriſt to take his Bellows and his Fan to blow up the ſmall ſparks in the dead aſhes, that they may grow into a flame of Love.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Take alſo a proſpect of thoſe Treaſures of Tranſcendent goodneſs, thoſe heaps of Infinite Perfections, that are ſtored up in God, the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſe Ocean of love and ſweetneſs, that fills every creek of Being; and look not upon a naked Chriſt, but as Inveſted with Perſonal Excellencies beyond compare, and ſo you will ſee how infinitely amiable he is in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:63142:20"/>6. But further take a ſweet view of the love of God in Chriſt, offering Pardon and Salvation to you with others, upon condition of believing, that ſo you may find your heart move reciprocally in love to God and Chriſt, and when once you find this in the heart, then you may conclude his ſpeciall Love to you, which will fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther increaſe your love to him. I do not ſay that your firſt Love to God muſt be kindled by the flames of his ſpecial Love to you, no, it is the proſpect of his goodneſs in himſelf, and of his common love and mercy to Sinners in tendring a Saviour, and not of his ſpecial ſaving Love to you, as actually enjoyed by you, that is the Incentive of your firſt love to him; for though you be bound to love God with a ſpecial Love, yet you are not bound to love him as one that ſpecially loveth you, untill you be indeed ſo beloved by him; other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe you were bound to believe a falſity, and to love God for that which is not. But if you once find
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:63142:20"/>
the ſpecial ſaving Love of God ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in your heart, working h<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i Grace in you, this will fire up your love to him, then you will be ready to ſay to your ſelf, what ſhall there be a Noon-day Sun-ſhine of Love and Grace upon me, a poor clod of Earth, and no reflexion of a Sun-beam? ſhall there be hot flamings forth from his Breaſt towards me, a worthleſs Worm, and not a ſpark in mine towards him? ſhall I not be moſt ingrateful if I do not offer up to him a flaming Sacrifice.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> Of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Obedience.</head>
               <p n="1">1. LIve in Univerſal Obedience to the Laws of God. This will follow upon that Love to God now Commended to you, as being the Daughter of it. Hence that ſpeech of our Saviour. <hi>If ye love me, keep my Commandments;</hi> John 14.15. Imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate that good Woman before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:63142:21"/>
(whoſe Name you bear) of whom it is ſaid, <hi>that ſhe walk'd in all the Commandments and Ordinances of the Lord blameleſs,</hi> Luk. 1.6. It's re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of poor weak Women, <hi>that they diligently follow every good Work,</hi> 1 Tim. 5.10. The ſound and healthy Chriſtian refuſeth no kind of Work that God enjoyns, be it never ſo hard and difficult, whereas the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſound crazy Hypocriſie, like a Man that hath ſome ſore Diſeaſe about him, will only ſet upon ſome eaſie Work, ſome ſlight duties of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but as for the more hard and difficult ones, as Wreſtling with the Old Man, running the Chriſtian Race, Mortification, Self-denial and ſtrict Holineſs, he paſſeth them over, here he makes a baulk in his Obedience, like a Husbandman that pulls aſide his Plough when he comes to a hard or ſtiff piece of Ground. How ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny are there that will comply with thoſe duties that are ſuitable to their own mind, and their own ends, who in others are very backward and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:63142:21"/>
take their liberty? Theſe are crook<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Sticks, that will not touch with Gods meaſure, they will pick and chuſe, it may be they will not be Wanton, but yet they will be Proud, they will not be unjuſt dealers, but yet they will be hard-hearted towards the Poor; it may be they will be Zealous in Worſhip, but yet Cenſorious and Uncharitable. Such give to God Bankrupt payment, a Noble in the Pound, part of his due.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Thoſe that are thus ſcant and partial in their Obedience, are guilty of the breach of the whole Law: <hi>For whoſoever ſhall keep the whole Law and offend in one Point, is guilty of all.</hi> Jam 2 10. Becauſe there is the ſame Authority in every Command, in one as well as another. One Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion not obſerved forfeiteth the whole Leaſe. O that this Principle may be Engraven in your Heart, that unleſs you be throughout Religious, your Religion is Vain!</p>
               <p n="3">3. In your Obedience therefore
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:63142:22"/>
take in the whole Compaſs and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of Religion, both Firſt and Second Table, and as Holy <hi>David, Have reſpect to all God</hi>'s <hi>Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> Pſal. 119.6. A gracious Heart anſwers the Law of God, as a Copy doth the Original, line for line, ſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable for ſyllable, letter for letter, and would not willingly receive or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit any Errata's; it's univerſally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to every Word of God. If you have a Gracious Spirit, you will not make any exception, you will not defalcate, or cut off any known Duty, you will not deſignedly clip off any part of God<hi>s</hi> Coin, any piece of that Service which hath Gods Stamp, and Superſcription on it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> Of Circumſpect Walking.</head>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>SEE that you walk circumſpectly, Eph.</hi> 5.15. It's not enough to walk in a good way, in an Univerſal courſe of duties, as to the matter of them, but
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:63142:22"/>
you muſt do it accurately and exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in a right manner. It's neceſſary that there be an Accurateneſs and Circumſpection obſerved in your Walking in the way to Heaven. Mind then your way very well, make it your work and buſineſs to go on in the Way, ſo as that you neither ſtumble in it, nor ſtep awry into by-paths. Obſerve exactly the ſteps of our fore-runner the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and tread therein. Walk by this Clue alone in this dark World, if you would neither go aſide, nor go crookedly in the way. The Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riner muſt know every Point of his Compaſs, otherwiſe he may endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger all. In your paſſage through the Sea of this World, you muſt mind the Word of God, and ſteer the Ship of your Soul by this Compaſs exactly: you muſt mind this Rule in all things that you do, you muſt Pray by Rule, Read, Hear, Meditate, give Alms, and examine your ſelf by Rule, Yea you muſt Eat, Drink, Sleep, Dreſs and Recreate your ſelf,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:63142:23"/>
and do every thing in every part of your converſation exactly by Rule.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Thoſe that are for their Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, for their vagaries and extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancies, they will cry out againſt all this ſtrictneſs and preciſeneſs, as a being Righteous over-much, and againſt all Zeal, as too feaveriſh, and will tell you that to be thus ſtrait-lac'd cannot be good for the ſpiritual birth: but alas, theſe never knew what this Scripture meant, <hi>Walk Circumſpectly,</hi> i. e. Strictly or Preciſely. Does not God who hath preſcribed you this ſtrictneſs, know what is beſt and moſt neceſſary for you? Let People think what they will, certainly without ſtrictneſs they can never be ſaved. <hi>The way to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven is a ſtrait gate, and there muſt be a ſtriving to enter into it,</hi> Luke 13.24. Salvation is not to be got with a wet finger, you cannot climb to Heaven with a little lazy and yawning Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. It's very dangerous trifling in Religion, and doing the Work of
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:63142:23"/>
God to halves. <hi>Curſed is he that doth the work of the Lord deceitfully,</hi> or neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently, <hi>Jer.</hi> 48.10. If you may have too much godlineſs, then you may have too much of Heaven and Bleſſedneſs.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It requires a great deal of cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpection and care to walk aright in the way to Heaven: You muſt be ſo exact here, as to avoid all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions and appearance of evil, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.22. and to keep your ſelf unſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the World; <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.27. You muſt be ſo careful, as not to contract any ſtain, or ſpot upon your Soul. A neat Lady in the dirty Streets, goes very cautiouſly and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpectly, obſerves her feet, picks out the cleaneſt way, takes accurate care to avoid every foul ſtep, holds up her Garment, that it may not be ſoil'd, or get the leaſt ſpot of dirt. Thus a neat Soul makes ſtrait paths for its feet; it makes ſtrait ſteps, and goes by a ſtrait Rule; conſiders its ways, and deſires God to order them; looks to its Garments, ſo as
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:63142:24"/>
not to defile them, or get the leaſt ſpot thereon. Are we not all under the exact and curious Eye of Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſcience, which marks all our ſteps, and ponders all our goings? had we not need therefore to walk circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectly, and to abſtain from all ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of evil?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> Of Dying daily.</head>
               <p n="1">1. DIE daily unto ſin. This is an excellent way to live well. Mortifie your corruptions; crucifie ſin within you. That your Soul may be in health, you muſt be in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued courſe of Phyſick all your life: for ſo long as you have this body of ſin, this corrupt nature about you, you will ſtill have matter to purge out.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Now that you may do this work of Mortification thoroughly, you muſt ſtrike at the whole body of ſin, the whole corrupt frame of heart, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:63142:24"/>
called Original Sin, which moſt perſons ſo little look at, and ſo little confeſs to God, as if they had no cauſe to be humbled for it. The ſharp Knife of mortifying Grace doth not only cut off ſome members or acts of ſin, but endeavours to cut off the very body of ſin, to take out the Core, ſo that the Ulcer may not break out again. You may reſtrain actual ſins, but you never mortifie them till corrupt nature within be ſubdued. Reſtraining actual ſins alone, is but violently to keep the Bladder under water, which will be mounting up again; but let corrupt Nature be wounded, and then you prick the bladder of ſin, and ſo it will ſink. Mortifying Grace makes ſuch a wound within, that the very life of corrupt Nature runs out by degrees. If an Impoſthume breaks, there's an endeavour not only to bring up all the matter in it, but to get hold of the very Bag alſo, otherwiſe the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient may die of it preſently, or it may gather again. When you become
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:63142:25"/>
ſenſible of ſin, and ſeriouſly convinced of it, the Impoſthume begins to break; oh labour then to pluck up Original Sin, or Corrupt Nature, which is the very Bag of the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſthume, that if poſſible it may not gather again. This is the very heart and root of ſin. If the heart be wounded and die, all the members die with it. If the root be grubb'd up, all the branches wither.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Think not that your Soul is in a healthy condition, till you find every ſin dying in you. In true Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification every ſin conſumes and pines away: As in a Hectick, there is a Conſumption not only of one member, but of all. The Phyſick that Chriſt gives to make ſin die in us, is not an Elective, that purgeth out one humour only, but it's an Univerſal Medicine, that works on all. If you leave one ſin, and have a heart hankering after another, you are but in <hi>Benhadad</hi>'s condition, who recovered of one Diſeaſe, but fell into another that proved mortal. It's
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:63142:25"/>
the Cuſtom of ſome Indians to value themſelves by the number of heads which they have cut off. If you would judge aright of your ſelf, ſee how many heads of ſin you have cut off, whether you have ſo cut off the head of every ſin, that it reign no more in you.</p>
               <p n="4">4. In your endeavour after the death of every ſin, you muſt eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially labour after the death and mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification of ſpiritual ſins, which like a Hectick, are moſt dangerous, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe moſt difficultly diſcovered; theſe lie cloſe in the heart unſeen. Pride of heart, and Self-love, (which is the very heart and quinteſſence of Unregeneracy) as are an Impoſthume more dangerous, becauſe ſo inward and indiſcernible. When the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſthume is within the breaſt, you cannot think to cure it by laying a Plaiſter to the skin; your application muſt here be made to the heart. Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Patients complain more of that Diſeaſe which is moſt apparent, than they do of that which is moſt malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:63142:26"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> Of Repentance.</head>
               <p>EXerciſe daily Repentance from dead works. I add this to the former Advice, becauſe it is by Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance unto life (as the Apoſtle calls it, <hi>Acts</hi> 11.18.) that ſin is mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified and made to die: Now this Repentance is a mourning after a godly manner, for ſins paſt, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volving fiducially in the ſtrength of Chriſt to forſake all ſin hereafter. I ſay, it is a mourning after a godly manner; which hath theſe following properties in it.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It is a great and bitter mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; it's not an eaſie grief or a mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Eye only, but it's a mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the heart, which is the heart of mourning. It's not ſuperficial tears, but the deep ſorrow of the heart, that will waſh away ſin. I have read a Story, that one of the Queſtions which the Queen of <hi>Sheba</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:63142:26"/>
to King <hi>Solomon</hi> was this; She having brought before him a company of Children, both Males and Females, all alike apparelled, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded of him which were the Boys, and which were the Girls, which he thus decided; he cauſed them all to waſh in a Baſon of Water, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd which rubb'd more hard, and thoſe he ſet aſide for the Boys; and thoſe that waſht more tenderly and ſoftly, he determined to be the Girls. Thoſe that would waſh away the filth of ſin, muſt not, like thoſe of that ſofter Sex, do it eaſily and tenderly, but muſt exerciſe a maſculine ſpirit, and rub hard (like thoſe of the harder and rougher Sex) to ſcour the Soul. It's not to be done by a ſlight Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance; there muſt be a great deal of pains taken to cleanſe the heart from ſin. And therefore Repentance is generally miſtaken, while it is thought to be nothing elſe, but a being ſorry for ſins committed, and a wiſhing they had not been done. Such ſlight Penitents can be ſorry to day,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:63142:27"/>
and ſin again to morrow, and yet think they have truly repented.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Mourning after a godly manner is a grief ſpringing from the bowels of love to God: the ſtronger the ſtream is, the more there is of the fountain; and the ſtronger the ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for ſin is, the more there is of God. A true Penitent finds a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple within him, that carries him out to a mourning for ſin: But an unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate man is rather forced upon it, by ſome extrinſick motives, as fear of Hell, than carried to it out of the proper and peculiar inclination of his own heart.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It's ſuch a ſorrow as changes the heart and life; there's a ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the inward man, and a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of the outward converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion going along with it. This ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for ſin conſumes the ſin that bred it, as the Worm doth the Wood that bred it.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It's accompanied with an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal hatred of ſin, an utter abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency of every iniquity. The Dove
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:63142:27"/>
(as they ſay) which hates the Hawk, hates every Feather of it. A true Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent ſo abhors ſin, that he hates eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry plume and feather, every branch of it, he would have the very me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of <hi>Amalek,</hi> blotted out; he hath a deadly hatred to the whole tribe of ſin, the whole ſtock and kind, to every member of that curſed family of ſin; he hates the very occaſions of ſin, which are only the harbingers and ſpokes-men of it, and will give them no entertainment, but thruſts them out of doors: He ſo hates ſin, that he longs to be rid of it. The Apoſtle cries out as one tied to a dead carcaſs, or tired with the Chains of a grievous bondage; <hi>O wretched man that I am, who ſhall deliver me from the body of this death! Rom.</hi> 7.14. He here cries out againſt the ſinfulneſs of Nature, and hates, and would be rid of that, as well as ſinfulneſs of Life. If you mourn only for actual ſins, you only cleanſe the ſtreams, and let the ſpring continue muddy and noiſome, which will ſoon ſend forth new ſtreams of the ſame nature.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:63142:28"/>But further; Repentance is not only a mourning for ſins paſt, but a fiducial Reſolution to forſake all for the future. I call it a fiducial Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, <hi>i. e.</hi> a Reſolution of Faith; for it is not an ordinary Reſolution that will prove one to be a true Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent; we have very revolting, ſlip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery hearts, apt to return to ſin, and therefore had need to take up ſtrong and fiducial Reſolutions in the ſtrength of Chriſt, to fortifie our hearts againſt ſin. Crazy Timber in a Building muſt be well Crampt with Iron Bars to keep it from yielding: And broken Bones had need of ſtrong filleting to bind them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>Take heed that you do not defer your Repentance, or adjourn it to another day: It's very dangerous ſo to do: Therefore I deſire you with all poſſible earneſtneſs, for the Love of God, and of your precious Souls, ſet upon this duty preſently. Do not ſay within your ſelf, I am young, and it's time enough to do it hereafter.
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:63142:28"/>
Remember Death comes riding Poſt, and though ſometimes he change Horſes, firſt come on one Diſeaſe, and leaving that, after come on ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; yet oftentimes he doth not change, but comes on one ſingle Horſe, and takes away at the firſt Sickneſs; and then, as you will but have little time to repent, ſo little aptneſs or diſpoſition thereunto, when Sickneſs hath once arreſted you. Oh how unfit will you then be to turn to God, when you can ſcarce turn your ſelf in your Bed! Let me therefore give you the Counſel that a Rabbin gave one of his Scholars, <hi>Repent a day before you die;</hi> and the Scholar thereupon thinking, that he ſhould have time enough, then he bade him repent to day, for thou knoweſt not but thou mayeſt be dead to morrow.</p>
               <p>But is not this (it may be ſaid) a hard painful Life to be every day re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penting? No, when it is done every day, it ſoon grows an eaſie work. The good Huſwife that ſcours her
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:63142:29"/>
Plate often, hath an eaſier task of it every day than other.</p>
               <p>But is not this a ſad and melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Life for to be always mourning and repenting? No, <hi>Tears of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,</hi> ſaith holy <hi>Bernard, are ſweeter than all worldly Joy.</hi> Repentance is a moſt ſweet Grace, and hath much comfort in it. The day of Expiation in the Old Law was a day of mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, yet the <hi>Jubilee</hi> was always to be proclaimed on that day. The day of mourning for ſin is a day of Expiation of ſin, and God then proclaims a <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilee</hi> to the Soul in the pardon of it. But further to take off this Objection, and to give a fuller Anſwer thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, I ſhall add the next following Advice.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> Of making Religion a delight.</head>
               <p>MAke Religion your great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light and Recreation. <hi>Delight your ſelf in the Lord, Pſal.</hi> 37.4. Or as the Apoſtle enjoyns, <hi>Rejoyce in the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:63142:29"/>
Lord alway, and again I ſay rejoyce, Phil.</hi> 4.4. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.16. Take delight in God himſelf, in his infinite Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies and Perfections, in his Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Love, and Mercy, in his Word and Works, in his Commands, and in his Promiſes, in his Ways, and in his Heaven, which he hath prepared for Souls. This, and my laſt Advice for a daily mourning for ſin, are no way inconſiſtent, but lovingly meet and kiſs each other. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves, that <hi>David</hi> the great mourner in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> was alſo the chief finger in <hi>Iſrael.</hi> As with one Eye we look down to our ſins, ſo we mourn; but as with the other Eye, <hi>i. e.</hi> the Eye of Faith, we look up to God, and his Mercy pardoning ſin upon Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, ſo we rejoyce. Godly ſorrow makes pardoning Mercy taſte the ſweeter, and cauſeth greater joy and delight in God. Muſick upon the Water ſounds louder, and is much ſweeter than upon the Land. Joy upon the Waters of Godly Sorrow is moſt ſweet and pleaſant. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:63142:30"/>
calls ſorrow for ſin the Mother of Joy. I aſſure you God never com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded ſorrow for ſin barely for it ſelf, but only in order unto joy.</p>
               <p n="2">2. God would not have any of his People lead ſad drooping and melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly Lives, for thereby they would diſhonour their heavenly Father, and diſparage his Houſe keeping, as if there were not Bread enough in their Fathers houſe, but rather a want of Neceſſaries there. Yea it would make the World ready to think that he were a hard Maſter toward them, and Jeſus Chriſt an unkind Husband. If a Wife be always ſad, and ſit puling and whining, will not every one be ready to ſay, that ſhe hath a bad Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band? This Sackcloth doth not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Court of the King of Saints, nor beſeem thoſe that live within it. Spiritual Chearfulneſe is that which becomes Religion, ſets a gloſs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and makes it ſhine gloriouſly, and look moſt amiably in the Eyes of the World, and may cauſe them to fall to love with it.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:63142:30"/>3. But whatſoever the Wor think of Religion, it is not of a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy temper, but of a ſanguine complexion. It may well ſay to them, Call me no more <hi>Marah, i. e.</hi> Bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; but call me <hi>Naomi,</hi> which ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies Pleaſantneſs; for it is of all others the moſt pleaſant and delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom Life, <hi>i. e.</hi> in reſpect of inward complacency and gladneſs, though not in reſpect of paſſionate joy or mirth. <hi>All her ways are ways of pleaſantneſs, and all her paths are peace, Prov.</hi> 3.17. Thus the way of Religion is ſtrawed with Roſes, with inward peace and tranquillity. Walking in the fear of the Lord, and in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts of the Holy Ghoſt, are claſpt and laid together; <hi>Acts</hi> 9.31. Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians have meat to eat that the World knows not of. <hi>What means this Muſick,</hi> ſaid the Elder Brother of the returning Prodigal? There's the White-Stone, and the New Name, that none know but they that have it; <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.17. There's hidden Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah for their Souls to feaſt upon.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:63142:31"/>4. And indeed how can a believing Soul that walks cloſely with God chuſe but rejoyce, when it is always in the preſence of God and Chriſt? <hi>Can the Children of the Bride-chamber mourn while the Bridegroom is with them? Matth.</hi> 9.15. It is reported, that our Saviour, when he was on the Earth, had ſuch a chearful Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, that the Jews that lived in his days, when they found themſelves ſad and melancholy, would ſay to one another, <hi>Come let us go and look upon</hi> Mary <hi>'s Son that we may be chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful.</hi> How true that is I know not; but this I am ſure, that looking upon Jeſus Chriſt by an Eye of Faith, will make a Soul rejoyce abundantly. <hi>Tho' now you ſee him not, yet believing you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce, with joy unſpeakable and full of glory;</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.8. Joy comes in by believing. Actings of Faith will cauſe Jeſus Chriſt to ſet abroach this Royal Wine of Joy for you, which will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be a-tilt, but alway run freſh while you act Faith, to draw. A be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving Soul hath a Bird in its own
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:63142:31"/>
boſom, that makes moſt ſweet and pleaſant Melody. Faith ſpies out God's Love in all things, ſees all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidential Diſpenſations come from God as a Token of Love, and ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyceth in all. When a Wife re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveth but a ſmall thing from her Husband abroad, as a Token of Love, ſhe rejoyceth more in it, than in forty times more which ſhe had at home before. But moſt of all Faith ſees Love of God ſhine forth in the Gifts of Grace, and Priviledges of Heaven. Hath God given you the rich Jewel of Grace, a Patent for Heaven, a Grant of the Priviledges of his Court, the Right of Adoption to the being a Daughter of God? You have abundant cauſe to rejoyce and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph in him, and to glory in the God of your Salvation.</p>
               <p n="5">5. You ſee what kind of joy and delight it is, that I have here com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to you: It is not an Enthu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtick joy or delight, through irra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional raptures, which reaſon can give no account of; but it's a rational,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:63142:32"/>
ſolid complacency of the Soul in God; nor is it a meer ſenſual joy. It's not the joy of thoſe merry ones of the Age, that ſpend their Life in vain and ſinful pleaſures, whoſe mirth is madneſs (as the Wiſe man calls it; <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 2.2.) Mad men will laugh, and hoop, and hollow, as if they were full of joy; but who knows not that their condition is very ſad? <hi>In the midſt of laughter the heart is ſad, and the end of that mirth is heavineſs; Prov.</hi> 14.13. Do not the jollieſt ſinners find a damp after all their mirth? and alas their mirth will laſt but a while; their feaſt will be ſoon over; the cloth will be ſhortly drawn, the mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick ſhall ceaſe to play at their doors, and then nothing ſhall be heard, but lamentable out-cries, bitter wailing, and gnaſhing of the Teeth for ever.</p>
               <p>I have been the longer on this, that I might keep you from that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice againſt Religion, which is in the hearts of moſt, as if it were a ſad and a melancholy life; as if the bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter herb of Grace would poiſon the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:63142:32"/>
flower of all their Mirth. And for the ſame reaſon I ſhall add another Advice a-kin to this.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi> Of Praiſe and Thankfulneſs to God.</head>
               <p n="1">1. LIve a Life of Praiſe and Thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs to God. This inclines the Soul to a holy rejoycing in God. Let him have your admiring Praiſes continually. O ſteep your thoughts in the Love and Mercies of God! Say often with your ſelf, O what hath God done for me! what great Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies hath he offered and tendred to my Soul? what a mercy is it that I am alive? that he hath bore with me thus long? and waited for my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance? what aſtoniſhing riches of Love and Free Grace is it that I am on this ſide Hell, and that there is an Alſufficient Saviour provided for me? I'll therefore live to the praiſe of his Glory, and bear witneſs to his tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendent Excellency.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:63142:33"/>2. Give God both tongue and heart to praiſe him. Anatomiſts ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, that the tongue of man is tyed to the heart by a double ſtring. May not this intimate that God would have the tongue, as well as the heart, a ſtringed Inſtrument of his Praiſe? But yet he regards not the Praiſes of the tongue at all, if you do not make melody in your heart unto him. What doth God require of you for all his mercies and loving-kindneſſes, but only praiſe? Some hold their Lands by paying the Rent of a Pepper-corn, or the like. We hold all that we have from God, who requires only that we ſhould pay this poor Qui<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> rent a Pepper-corn of Thankfulneſs, which if we pay daily to him, he will give in more mercies. Trumpeters delight to ſound where they may have an Eccho, and God to give where he may have an Eccho of Praſe. God is much delighted with the praiſes of his People; he likes well a thankful frame of heart; and indeed the heart is never in a better
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:63142:33"/>
frame, than when it's tuned into a thankful Note.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Labour very much to get your ſelf moulded into this excellent frame of a thankful and praiſeful ſpirit. Do you love and affect mirth and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure? let me then prevail with you to endeavour ſeriouſly to get this Truth engraven as a Principle in your breaſt, that you will never find more pure and clarified pleaſure, more ſweet delight, more raviſhing joy, than when you are in a God-praiſing, and a Chriſt-admiring frame. <hi>David</hi>'s mouth is filled as with marrow and fatneſs; <hi>i. e.</hi> with the moſt ſweet and delicious pleaſure when he praiſes the Lord; <hi>Pſal.</hi> 62.5. Yea this will be bleſſedneſs to you. <hi>Bleſſed</hi> (ſaith that holy Pſalmiſt) <hi>are they that dwell in thy houſe, for they will be ſtill praiſing thee; Pſal.</hi> 84.4. By being thus em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed, you will hold a Conſort with Heaven, and fill up the Muſick there.</p>
               <p n="4">4. And becauſe you are unable by all your Songs of Thanks and Praiſe to reach unto that height of Praiſe,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:63142:34"/>
which the Love and Mercies of God call for from you, even a Note above <hi>Ela,</hi> ſuch a high Note as would crack all your Strings, all your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties to get up unto; therefore call to Angels and Arch-Angels, and all the Quire in the Cathedral of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, to ſing glory, honour and praiſe to him that ſits upon the Throne, and to the Lamb for ever and ever.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XII.</hi> Of Humility.</head>
               <p n="1">1. LEarn to live humbly before God. This will help very much to advance that Praiſe and Thankfulneſs that I have now been praiſing to you. The humble Canaa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitiſh, how thankful would ſhe be for a Crum falling from the Table of Mercy? <hi>Matth.</hi> 15. A dram of Mercy will then weigh very heavy with you, when you look upon your ſelf as the very duſt of the ballance.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Prophet <hi>Micah, chap.</hi> 6.8.
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:63142:34"/>
declaring what is good, and what the Lord requires of us, gives this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction; <hi>Walk humbly with thy God.</hi> We put on our beſt Robes when we are to be taken into familiar converſe with great perſons: And therefore that you may walk with the great God, and converſe with him, be clothed with Humility, as the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> exhorts, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.5. This is a plain, but a very comely and neat Sute of Apparel. The Greek word that the Apoſtle uſeth in that place, ſeems to allude to the Knots or Rib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands that Women tie about them for Ornament. Humility is an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Ribband, that doth not only adorn the Soul, but ties all the Graces together on a knot; it's the ſtring of all thoſe precious and goodly Pearls, which if it break, they are all ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered. If you ſuffer Pride to break this ſtring, your loſe all your Virtues. When the low Violet of Humility withers, all your other Flowers will die. Hence <hi>Bernard,</hi> who calls Faith the Mother, ſtiles Humility the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:63142:35"/>
Nurſe of all Graces. God will give all Grace to the humble; 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.5. The richeſt Wine is laid up in the loweſt Cellars. The graces and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts of the Spirit are not laid in the high and lofty heart. It's ſaid of <hi>Sancta Clara,</hi> that ſhe was but once in all her life tickled with the thoughts of Pride, and ſhe felt not the comforts of the Spirit of twenty years after. Without this Garment of of Humility the Soul is naked and thread-bare. It's a Grace of the greateſt worth, and yet it will coſt you the leaſt to keep it.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Shew your Humility by your ſweet contentedneſs with that condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which the Wiſdom of God ſhall aſſign you; ſhew it by your being ſo far from over-valuing your ſelf, that you do entertain mean and low thoughts of your ſelf; and let it alſo appear by your ſetting light by the eſteem of others, and by patient bearing all their ſlights. It's hard indeed to be cut in this Vein, and not to bleed very ſore, if not deadly.
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:63142:35"/>
Shew your Humility alſo by aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doning bravery or coſtlineſs of Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parel for oſtentation.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Now that you may become humble, and keep your ſelf ſo, ſtudy much the Corruption of Nature, and to know your ſelf: Say often to your ſelf, O what a vile ſinful Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture have I! how full of corruption, which makes my life full of ſin? how empty am I of all good? in what a Bankrupt condition is my poor Soul? And if you would in this caſe take a right and impartial view of your ſelf, there is one falſe Glaſs which you muſt avoid, which is the Glaſs of Self-love; this will repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent all fair to you, and make you ſeem to your ſelf better than you are: This is it which makes ones own pride, and vanity, and unbelief, and unholineſs ſeem to be a little ſin, a tolerable fault, and not to deſerve damnation. It will make every com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Grace appear to be ſaving Grace, and a ſtate of Godlineſs; and every Duty a true mark of Regeneracy.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:63142:36"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIII.</hi> Of Meekneſs.</head>
               <p n="1">1. EXerciſe a meek ſpirit in all your converſe in the World. Would you be richly adorned? the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> will tell you how it may beſt be, and what is the beſt faſhion; and that is, <hi>the ornament of a meek and quiet ſpirit;</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.3, 4, 5. You may perhaps think that ſuch a meek de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment would be a derogation from your Credit; but ſee there, how God counts it an Ornament, better than that of wearing of Gold, or put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting on of coſtly Apparel; yea ſuch an Ornament as is in his ſight of great price. And it is the beſt faſhion alſo; <hi>v.</hi> 5. <hi>for ſo holy women of old adorned themſelves.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Gratifie me your Father in this ſmall requeſt; Never provoke others unto Paſſion, neither be you by others provoked thereunto. But what, ſhall I be trampled upon? no, it will be
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:63142:36"/>
your greateſt glory and honour to paſs by an affront. A cool ſpirit is an excellent ſpirit; according as it is in the marginal reading of <hi>Prov.</hi> 17. <hi>v.</hi> 27. But ſhall I not then be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted a Fool? No, it will be your beſt Wiſdom: <hi>For the Wiſdom which is from above is gentle, peaceable, eaſie to be intreated; Jam.</hi> 3.17. A gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious meek ſpirit will put up many an affront, and never rage. Full Veſſels will bear many a knock and ſtroke, and yet make no noiſe: But if there be envying and ſtrife in you, are you not carnal? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.3. This wiſdom comes not from above, but is earthly, ſenſual, deviliſh; <hi>Jam.</hi> 3.15. Theſe overflowings of the Gall, are cauſed by corrupt and noxious humours within. Let me perſwade you then to take this gentle Medicine, this grace of Meekneſs, which will ſtop thoſe bitter overflowings, and effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally cure the burning Feaver of Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which is cauſed thereby, and readily heal an angry Sore. This cool ſpirit will either prevent ſparks from
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:63142:37"/>
kindling, or ſoon quench them. Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is a ſoft and gentle breath, a ſmooth and pleaſant fann, that cools the Paſſions. It's ſoft Wooll that breaks the force of Cannon-ſhot, that damps the fierceſt anger.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIV.</hi> Of Living in Love and Charity to all.</head>
               <p n="1">1. LIve in Love and Charity to your Neighbour. Be careful to get this grace engraven on your breaſt, and as it were moulded into your very Nature. Live in this Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Love; let the acting there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of be ſo natural and familiar to you, that he that runs may read this New Commandment, which Chriſt left, of loving one another, written in you, as it were in Letters of Gold. Oh how main a part of Religion and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs lies in this duty of Love? I do not know through all the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament any one duty, ſo much incul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated and preſt on, as this of Love;
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:63142:37"/>
no ſtring ſo much beat upon, as if it made the beſt Muſick, and ſweeteſt Harmony in Chriſtian Religion.</p>
               <p n="2">2. You muſt love all, even the moſt wicked in the World, as having the natural Image of God, or the marks of his Perfection in the Rational Soul. <hi>David</hi> indeed profeſt his hatred of God's Enemies, but it was (according to the ordinary gloſs) of their ſins, not of their perſons. That effect of Lightning in breaking the Sword, and not bruiſing the Scabbard, is account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as one of Natures great Myſteries. But this heavenly flame of Love and Charity, ſeems much more myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and admirable in its operations, whilſt it would by all means keep ſafe, and preſerve the perſon of our vicious Neighbour and Enemy, when it hath a deadly hatred unto, and a deſire to deſtroy his Vices.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Though you love all, yet your beſt and choiceſt Love muſt be to the Saints, in whom the Moral Image of God, which conſiſts in righteouſneſs and true hollneſs (and is the ſpecial
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:63142:38"/>
Loadſtone of Love) doth ſhine and ſparkle forth. In the parallel Lines which are drawn from the Circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the Center, they all draw to it, and the nearer the Center, the nearer they are to one another. God is the Center of Love, and the nearer we come to him, the nearer are we to one another in ſpiritual Affection. There's a Conſanguinity of Graces among the Saints, and therefore the greateſt Love, as there is among per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of the ſame blood and kindred: They are all the Children of God by Faith.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Let this Love put you upon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ready to do all the good you can, as you have opportunity, but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to thoſe that are of the houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold of Faith. Let the Errand on which <hi>Jeſſe</hi> ſent <hi>David,</hi> be your great buſineſs in the World. Look how thy Brethren fare. Conſider the Poor ſo as to relieve them. Deny your ſelf Superfluities, that you may ſupply the Poor with Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries. The Poor are God's Ward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>robe;
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:63142:38"/>
you cannot hang up your Riament in a better place.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XV.</hi> How to manage your Converſe in Company.</head>
               <p n="1">1. LET that grace of Love and Charity commended to you in the former Chapter, ſteer and influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence you in your Civil Converſe in all Companies. Let it be as a bridle to your tongue, to reſtrain your ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing evil of others, and to curb all cenſuring. <hi>Take him</hi> (ſaith holy Mr. <hi>Baxter) that ſpeaks evil of another to you, to be Satan's Meſſenger, intreat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you to hate your Brother, or to abate your Love.</hi> Let me then warn and caution you, not to run upon Satans Errand, or to do his Meſſage. And conſider that this ſpeaking evil of others, is the great Make-bate, the grand Incendiary that raiſeth up flames, kindles hatred and malice, and damps all Love and Affection.
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:63142:39"/>
It's the Sluce of diſſention and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, the great Inlet of jarrs and ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſities, of quarrels and contentions in all Companies. And as for cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring of others, how familiar is it with thoſe of your Sex, when they come together, to run diviſion in the Cenſures of other perſons, either for their entertainments, their garb and dreſſing, their outward behaviour and geſtures, or ſome ſuch trifles? alway finding fault, and often making (as Coneys do holes in the Rocks) where they cannot find; therefore do you mind your ſelf only; look within your ſelf, within your own heart; in this reſpect keep at home, like a good Huſwife; be much with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in doors, within your own boſom, to ſpy what fault there is, and go not abroad in uncharitable Cenſures of others. In the Twilight we can ſee to read without doors, when we cannot within: We cannot ſee the ſwellings in our own hearts, when we can eaſily ſpy ſmall Pimples in another; we can ſee the Mo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e in
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:63142:39"/>
anothers Eye, when we cannot the Beam in our own.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Be watchful when you are in Company, that you contract no harm thereby. The Bee in the midſt of the Hive full of clinging ſtuff, yet keeps her wings untoucht with it. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed vain Company hath uſually a very ſtrong force, to make us imitate their geſtures, words and actions; we uſually learn our Pronunciation, our <hi>Shib<gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>th,</hi> and our Geſtures and Gate, by our Company. You can ſcarce come any where, but there is ſome white Wall, or ſome black Hood, ſo that you ſhall carry ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing away with you. But the greateſt danger is from carnal Friends and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations; theſe indeed are the great Impediments in the way to Heaven. Many in all probability had been ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and gracious perſons, if they had had better Kindred, and lived where Godlineſs had been encouraged, and good Examples given thereunto. O it is a very ſad thing to be near to them, whoſe nearneſs will remove you
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:63142:40"/>
further from God! Be therefore ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding careful, to keep your ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Watch in your Company; and labour ſo to live in the World, as not to partake of the corrupt and ſinful humours of it: As Mother Pearls live in the Sea, not taking in one drop of Salt Water into their Shells.</p>
               <p n="3">3. But yet as much as poſſible may be, avoid joyning your ſelf with any Acquaintance, except ſuch by whom you may be made better. The Royal Pſalmiſt begins his firſt Pſalm with the bleſſedneſs of that perſon, who hath not walkt in the company of the ungodly. Diamonds will not cement with Rubbiſh.</p>
               <p n="4">4. In all Converſe in any Company, let ſome good words fall from you, that may tend to make them bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Let your Lips (like the Spouſes in the <hi>Canticles</hi>) drop as the Honey-comb; diſtil ſome ſweetneſs, ſome ſavoury and wholſom words. A word ſpoken in ſeaſon may thro' God's bleſſing tend to the eternal wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of a Soul. A good Woman riding
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:63142:40"/>
with her Husband in a great Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, which much affrighted him, and being askt by him what the reaſon was, why ſhe was not at all afraid, returned this ſweet and holy Anſwer; <hi>Becauſe it is my Fathers Voice.</hi> And this one ſeaſonable word proved the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of his Converſion to God.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Be ſure to avoid all vain diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe and idle chatt, which is the feminine malady; and let your words be few and well conſidered before you ſpeak. Remember that aſtoniſhing ſpeech, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.36. <hi>That of every idle word, that you ſhall ſpeak, you ſhall give an account thereof at the day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVI.</hi> How to manage Solitarineſs.</head>
               <p n="1">1. VVHen you are ſolitary and alone, take heed of the creeping in of vain thoughts, which are then moſt apt to ſwarm. Oh it is incredible to think what a multitude
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:63142:41"/>
of vain thoughts, run through the vain mind in an hour; perhaps as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as there be Sands in an Hour-glaſs. O what pity is it that this noble Soul ſhould be ſo idle, either doing no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, or to ſo little purpoſe! It's an evil heart, that like Jett, draws to it ſelf nothing but Straws. O how much is it to be lamented, that this golden Mill of the Soul, ſhould ſpend it ſelf in grinding Chaff for its Enemy, the great deſtroyer of Mankind! <hi>O waſh thy heart from wickedneſs, how long ſhall thy vain thoughts lodge within thee? Jer.</hi> 4.14.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Entertain ſome ſhort diſcourſes with God, or with your ſelf when you are alone. You never need com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of Melancholy and Solitarineſs in want of Company, when you may make your ſelf company enough; for you may then hold diſcourſe with God and your own Soul. A Child of God is never leſs alone, than when moſt alone, becauſe he hath God uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally with him, who is the beſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany. That good Heathen Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:63142:41"/>
                  <hi>Epictetus,</hi> could ſolace himſelf in his Solitarineſs in Baniſhment, with theſe thoughts, that Divine Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quies and Conferences were to be had every where with God. O learn to converſe with God in your moſt ſolitary Retirements. Say to God, <hi>I will ſet thee always before me, Pſal.</hi> 16.8. Or you may profitably uſe ſome diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes with your ſelf, ſome Divine Soliloquies; you may call your Soul aſide to her withdrawing Room; you may commune with your own heart in your Chamber, as the Pſalmiſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth it; <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4.4. But not as the Fool in the Goſpel did, ſinging a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure lullaby to his Soul; <hi>Soul, thou haſt much goods laid up for many years, eat, drink, and be merry; Luk.</hi> 12.19. But after the example of the devout Pſalmiſt, ſinging a holy reſt to his Soul; <hi>Return unto thy Reſt, O my Soul! for God hath dealt bountifully with thee; Pſal.</hi> 116.7. Or if you have a troubled ſpirit, then you may talk to your ſelf in a way of challenge, or chiding ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtulation; <hi>Why art thou caſt down, O
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:63142:42"/>
my Soul! and why art thou diſquieted within me?</hi> As he did, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 42.5, 11. where he rallies up his Soul in that awakening Enquiry. And if after you ſee reaſon to alter your Note, and to give thanks for the ſcattering of that ſad Cloud by the Sun-ſhine of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doning Mercy and Love, then you may ſet your Affections in the ſame Key, in which the ſame holy Man's were in another Soliloquy, ſaying with him; <hi>Bleſs the Lord, O my Soul! and all that is within me bleſs his holy Name, who forgiveth all thine iniquities, and healeth all thy diſeaſes; Pſal.</hi> 103.1, 2, 3.</p>
               <p n="3">3. This courſe will much improve you in Piety and Holineſs; and this Retirement will help you to the moſt excellent Company, to the Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God and Chriſt, who will dwell in you; and the innumerable company of Angels and juſt men made perfect will be of the ſame Society with you. She that is not permitted to ſpeak in the Church, may thus preach to her ſelf, in her own pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Chapel, to her great benefit. I
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:63142:42"/>
mean that Sacred Chapel, which her Devotion hath built in her own heart.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVII.</hi> How to live in a Proſperous Condition.</head>
               <p n="1">1. LIve above withering Vanities, above all the ſmiles and blan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſhments of the World; let not your heart be glued to any creature com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts; look on them all as withered flowers, as dead things; let your heart be crucified to the World, and the World to it, looking upon it as a dead carcaſs, that hath no beauty or lovelineſs in it. If you profeſs your ſelf a Chriſtian, live at a higher rate than others. How unbecoming is it a Child of God to be puzling her ſelf about the World? A ſenſe of the Love of God would lift up your Soul above the ſweeteſt flowers and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights upon Earth, in all which there will be found nothing but Worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood and Gall in the latter end,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:63142:43"/>
nothing but vanity and vexation of ſpirit. It's only the Roſe of <hi>Sharon</hi> that is without prickles.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Proportion your duties accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to your mercies; the greater Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivings or Incomes you have from God, the greater muſt your Diſburſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Layings out for him be. Your Accounts muſt be according to the number and weight of your Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25. The Servant ſhould proportion his work according to his wages. The Tree brings forth fruit proportionable to the juyce and nouriſhment that the root ſucks from the Earth, and to the coſt that is beſtowed upon it. In the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial Law God required more coſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sacrifices from the Rich than from the Poor: A pair of Turtle Doves or two young Pigeons would have been accepted from the Poor, but not from the Rich. God was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed with <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> becauſe he rendred not according to the benefits received, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 23.25.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Improve all your proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:63142:43"/>
and lawful pleaſures to the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering of your delight in God. If that a proſperous condition ſhould afford you all the variety of Objects, which might be moſt delectable to the ſeveral ſenſes, uſe them only, as Stirrops, or as the advantage of a higher ground, to raiſe up your ſelf by to the thoughts of Heaven, and the delights thereof. Let your Soul take occaſion and advantage thence, to carry it ſelf up to the delightful thoughts of God, the giver of all theſe; as the Bird from the Tree takes the further flight: And ſo far as you can, make uſe of all your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in creature comforts to promote your delight in the Lord, and to drive away thoſe black Clouds of carnal fears and ſadneſſes of ſpirits, which are Enemies to your ſpiritual joy and delight. Thus you will prove your ſelf a good Chymical Chriſti<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, extracting a ſpiritual Quinteſſence out of theſe earthly and droſſy things; thus you turn Dung and Droſs into Gold and Pearls, mean and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:63142:44"/>
matters into high and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous things, and gain to your ſelf ſuch an <hi>Elixir</hi> as will refreſh the Soul, and fill it with Cordial Spirits. When you perceive and taſt the ſweetneſs and pleaſantneſs of theſe outward mercies, think ſeriouſly, if theſe be ſo ſweet and delightſom, how much more ſweet is God himſelf, who put all that ſweetneſs and pleaſantneſs therein?</p>
               <p n="4">4. As you love your Soul, let not your life be a life of pleaſure and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. If the Devil can but take you up with one pleaſure one day, and another vanity another, till the Hour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glaſs of your time be run out, he hath his end, and you are ruin'd for ever. Remember <hi>Dives,</hi> his life was a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual feaſt of pleaſure, (<hi>Luk.</hi> 16.19.) but death ſoon brought the Voider, and the Devil took away. O do not ride to Hell upon the back of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure! Can any think to dance with the Devil all day, and to ſup with Chriſt at night? <hi>Quies,</hi> which ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies Reſt, wants the plural number:
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:63142:44"/>
Flatter not your ſelf with dreams of having a Reſt in carnal pleaſures here, and everlaſting Reſt hereafter alſo.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVIII.</hi> How to manage an Afflicted Condition.</head>
               <p n="1">1. USE your beſt endeavours to get good by all the Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Croſſes that ſhall befal you. I know indeed it may be with Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians as with Meats; ſome are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in Sugar, as Cherries and Plums, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> others (as Beef) are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in Brine. But yet I think, you have more reaſon to fear the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of a proſperous, rather than the ſharp Brine of an adverſe condition. Bees are killed with Honey, but quickened with Vinegar. If you read your Bible through, you ſhall find that few of God's Children have gone through a proſperous condition, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being enſnared thereby, and rare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly find any but have been bettered by adverſity. In the Summer of proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity it's well if you be not Fly-blown.
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:63142:45"/>
In the budding Spring, and in the blooming Summer, then Pride and Vanity, Formality in Religion, and Satisfaction in Creature comforts will be apt to ſprout forth and taint you; but the ſharp Winter of Affliction will kill theſe Vermin. Sharp and bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter things are abſterſive, and cleanſe the body from many noxious and phlegmatick humours; whereas ſweet things, much uſed, do ſtuff up the paſſages of the body, and create many obſtructions. It's a high Character that is given of that Noble Perſon, that Mirrour of your Sex, the Lady <hi>Jane Gray,</hi> that ſhe ſo managed an af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted condition, that ſhe made Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry it ſelf ſeem amiable, and the Night-cloths of Adverſity did as much be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come her as her Day-dreſſing. God's Children are his Jewels, his rich Plate, which being ſcoured by Afflictions, look brighter; their Souls are bleacht and whitened in the Waters of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions. Theſe are the ſharp Lem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon that take off their Mill-dews. Chriſtians ſeldom come to be great
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:63142:45"/>
Scholars in the School of Chriſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Rod of Afflictions. Learn to value Afflictions as you do Phyſick, not according to the taſt and relliſh, but according to the profitable effects that it works. That is to be accounted a bleſſed Feaver that preſerves the Soul from everlaſting burnings.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If you be not better'd by God's Rod when he ſends it, take heed leſt he turn not his Rod into a Serpent, as <hi>Moſes</hi> Rod was. Is it not to be thought a dangerous ſymptom of God's rejection and that the Phyſician of our Souls is leaving us, when Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, which uſually are God's Phyſick to purge out our Diſeaſe, do cooperate therewith, and ſo encreaſe it? it's then to be feared that we ſhall hardly recover.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Improve all Afflictions for your ſpiritual good by Prayers, and actings of Faith in a Promiſe. 1. By Prayer. <hi>Is any afflicted? let him pray, Jam.</hi> 5.13. Afflictions may be ſaid to be improv'd by Prayer, theſe two ways; 1. By mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them a motive to put your ſelf on
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:63142:46"/>
Prayer. The Rod then doth the Child good, when it brings his ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born heart to his knees. God there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore lays his People on their backs, that he may make them to look up to Heaven. Every Croſs is an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanctified Croſs, that is not attended with Prayer. 2. By uſing Prayer as a means to help you againſt thoſe ſins, which are apt to accompany an af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted condition, as Impatience, Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and to fetch in thoſe graces which you have moſt need of therein, as Faith, Humility, Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, Contentment, Joy, and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to the Will of God. Prayer will cauſe theſe precious fruits to grow on the Croſs, and ſo it will be ſanctified to you.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Improve Afflictions by actings of Faith in the Promiſes. Afflictions are ſweetned to Believers, they are rolled up in Sugar, they are ſteept in Honey, ſanctified by the word of the Promiſe, that they ſhall work toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for good, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28. and yield the peaceable fruit of righteouſneſs,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:63142:46"/>
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.1. The Promiſe gives them a moſt delicious relliſh to Faith. Faith can make a ſoveraign Oil of theſe Scorpions to heal the Soul. Faith can turn Water into Wine, even the bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Waters of <hi>Marah</hi> into the Wine of Comfort.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIX.</hi> How to manage your Relative Condition.</head>
               <p n="1">1. BE earneſt in Prayer to the God of all Grace, to furniſh you with ſuitable Grace for the Relations you ſtand in. Hath God called you to be a Wife? pray for the ſpirit of a Wife. There's no Relation that we enter into, but it calls for new duties from us. No Relation but hath its pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar temptations and ſins, to which it is prone. Conſider then what are your Relation-temptations, and your Relation-ſins, and what are your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation-duties, and pray for ſtrength againſt thoſe particular temptations and ſins, and for thoſe particular
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:63142:47"/>
duties. No duties are more momen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, and yet none leſs obſerved uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally. It's a common fault to neglect our own work, and too much to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of others neglecting theirs; and ſo like Planets we eclipſe one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Many Wives are apt to pick quarrels, becauſe their Husbands do not their duties, when themſelves omit their own. And ſo many unna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Children complain of their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents for being ſo, when it is next door to an impoſſibility for a Patent to be unnatural. O mind well your Relation defects, and be very careful that Religion may form and mould your demeanour towards all your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations whatſoever. This will be your excellency; thus will you be like a fixed Star, ſhining in that proper Orb, in that very ſphere and ſtation, where God hath fixt you, without ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centrick motions.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If you would know how the caſe ſtands betwixt God and your Soul, conſider what you are in all your ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Relations, and how you manage
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:63142:47"/>
them. Judge not your ſelf ſo much by your praying, and hearing, and other duties of Religion in your general Calling, as a Chriſtian, as by the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of your Religion at home in your Relations Obſerve ſpecially how your Religion works in your Relative con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and the temptations thereof. She is not a good Woman, that is not a good Wife, or not a good Daughter.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Live in a free and chearful ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion and obedience to your Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band: You have this command given in ſeveral places of Scripture. <hi>Wives ſubmit your ſelves to your own Husbands, as unto the Lord; Eph.</hi> 5.22. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.18. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.1. This ſubmiſſion includes both Reverence and Obedience to the Husband, and this Obedience muſt be ſhewed both to his commands, his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, his reſtraints, and his rebukes; nay, if his rebukes ſhould turn to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilings, the Wife may not revile again; for that would be to ſhoot with the Devil in his own Bow; but ſhe may ſweetly admoniſh him in things that ſhe certainly knows to be ſinful and
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:63142:48"/>
hurtful. Your ſubjection doth not hinder you from provoking him to love and good works, as the Apoſtle uſeth the phraſe; <hi>Heb.</hi> 10 24. but yet even this provocation muſt be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out paſſion: You may lovingly admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh him thereunto, but with a care, that in ſo doing, you provoke him not to wrath, leſt you do like thoſe, who take hot water to heat the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach, and thereby enflame the Liver. The Wife in <hi>Nathan</hi>'s Parable is called a Lamb; ſhe muſt be a Lamb for meekneſs. The Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſaid, <hi>Ye were as Sheep going aſtray, but are now returned unto the Shepherd of your Souls;</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.25. He imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately adds in the next words; <hi>Ye Wives be in ſubjection to your own Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands.</hi> Wives are Chriſts Sheep, and muſt not be the Devils Shrews.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Is God calling you to be a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (having formed a work in you unſeen to any other Eye but his) take great care, that you give up, and ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly devote and dedicate the fruit of your womb to God, to be his Servants,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:63142:48"/>
ſo that all the Children that God ſhall give you, may be (as <hi>Bathſheba</hi> called <hi>Solomon</hi>) Children of your Vows. And in the educating of them, ſee that you be continually inſtilling and dropping into them the Milk of wholſom In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, that ſo it may be ſaid of you, as of <hi>Solomon</hi>'s virtuous Woman; <hi>her Children riſe up and call her bleſſed; Prov.</hi> 31.28. How careful have holy Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men been in theſe caſes? While <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nica</hi> the Mother of Saint <hi>Austin</hi> was with Child with him, ſhe did often devote him to the Chriſtian Religion, and the Service of the great God; and afterwards in his Education, ſhe ſo affectionately tendred the good of his Soul, that he was called the Child of her Prayers and Tears. It was <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy</hi>'s happineſs that he had a good Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and a good Grand-mother; for ſo he learned the Scriptures from a Child. And the Mother of holy <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard,</hi> as ſoon as her Children were born, gave them up to the Lord Jeſus, to be his Servants: And no leſs care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful was ſhe of of their Inſtructions, as
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:63142:49"/>
ſoon as they came to be capable there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and the ſucceſs was happy, in that all of them became holy Children of God. Children while young are moſt with the Mother, and in her company, and uſually have the moſt love to her, and therefore are the moſt likely to take her Inſtructions; therefore be you careful to improve that advantage. And begin betimes with them, ſo ſoon as you ſee the firſt buddings of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. Gardiners begin to graft at the firſt riſing of the Sap in the Spring, and when the Bud of the Stock firſt begins to ſwell and enlarge. The Wax, while it is ſoft and tender, will eaſily take Impreſſion. Labour by all means to imprint upon the Children that God ſhall give you, a ſtamp of Holineſs. <hi>Philip</hi> King of <hi>Macedon</hi> gave to one a piece of Metal, without any ſtamp, who after returned it again to the King with his Son <hi>Alexander</hi>'s Picture engraven on it, which very much pleaſed the King. You will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive your Children from God unpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſht, without any form; ſee that you
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:63142:49"/>
return them back to him with his Son Chriſts Image on them, which is the Image of Holineſs.</p>
               <p n="5">5. How ſadly accented an account have thoſe Mothers to give to God, who neglect giving of good Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions to their Children betimes? What a terrible ſpeech was that of a dying Lady to her ungodly Mother? <hi>It's too late now to ſpeak of God to me, I am going to Hell before, and you will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly follow after.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XX.</hi> How to manage all Natural and Civil actions religiouſly.</head>
               <p n="1">1. MAnage all your Natural and Civil actions by the Rules of Religion, making the very drift and ſcope of them all to be the pleaſing and glorifying of God. Let the Needle in the Compaſs of your Soul, ſtand directly and ſteddily to this Pole, God's Glory; and then you will ſteer your courſe aright. Mind this end,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:63142:50"/>
not only in acts of Devotion, and the direct duties of Religion, but in the courſe of your civil converſation.</p>
               <p n="2">2. And do not ſatisfie your ſelf with making God your end in the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral courſe of your life, but mind this end actually and expreſly in every ſolemn action of every day. If you eat or drink, do it not to gratifie your carnal ſenſe or appetite, but to preſerve your health, that by your health and ſtrength you may be better enabled to do God ſervice. And ſo in all your domeſtick affairs, level your Arrow at the ſame mark, aim at this White chiefly and ultimately, the Glory of God. Thus you will make both your Natural and Civil actions to ſlide into Religion, and become parts of God's ſervice. Thus you will ſerve God in your lying down, and in your riſing up, in your eating, drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſleeping, viſiting, journeying, and all other your lawful actions.</p>
               <p n="3">3. But I do not here bid you to mind this end actually in every ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary action throughout the whole day,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:63142:50"/>
or in every bit of Bread that you put in your mouth; this cannot be done; but yet you may do it in every ſolemn action of the day; you may at every meal when you ſit down actually and obſervedly mind this end, though not in every bit you eat. Or in a morning when you riſe, you may have a reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved intention to do all that day in the Name of God, and for his Glory; and you may by a ready unobſerved act of a ſtrong habit order all particulars that day to the ſame end, which you did actually propound to your ſelf at firſt riſing in the morning; and ſtill all the day do propound to your ſelf in the general habitual diſpoſition, frame, and purpoſe of the heart. Thus then, though the Glory of God, and good of the Soul, cannot be diſtinctly and actually intended in every ſingle action of the day; yet a ſincere habitual in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of God's Glory, well fixed and rivetted within, will be ſufficient to ſteer and influence all the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of that day into that end. As a man that ſets forward in a Journey
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:63142:51"/>
with a full intention to go to <hi>London,</hi> though he do not actually think of <hi>London</hi> in every ſtep that he takes, yet by virtue of the firſt ſettled intention, every particular ſtep is ordered to that end.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXI.</hi> Of ſpending of Time.</head>
               <p n="1">1. NEver do any thing meerly to paſs the time away. Neither make any Viſits, nor ſet upon any thing called Recreation, barely on that account. Time is too precious a Jewel, too valuable a Treaſure, to ſtudy how to get rid of it, as ſome do of an old Commodity that lies on their hands, that they cannot tell what to do with. God never gave us the leaſt pittance or moment of good to trifle away, but that we might do ſome time therein. What, can you have any time to paſs away, when many would give all they are worth but to draw out their breath one hour longer? As a great
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:63142:51"/>
Lady that cryed out on her Death-bed, <hi>All too late, a world of wealth for an inch of time.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Avoid all ſuch occaſions whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver as are expenſive of much time to no good purpoſe; as vain trickings and trimmings, tirings and dreſſings, too long needleſs viſits, peruſal of idle Books, or Treatiſes of vanity and folly, vain thoughts, fruitleſs diſcourſe, unneceſſary ſleep, uſeleſs Recreations, and idle Games. But it may be askt, Are not theſe things lawful? This one Queſtion ſends many to Hell; <hi>May I not do this?</hi> For we are moſt of all in danger by the uſe of lawful things, being here moſt apt to go beyond our bounds. There are more killed by Wine than there are by Poiſon. But why may not I do as the moſt perſons do, that are of my rank and quality? No; do not you ſet your Watch by the Town Clock, but by the Sun-Dial of the Scripture, the true and perfect Dial of the increated Sun. Make not your Neighbours, but the Scriptures the Rule of your Life.
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:63142:52"/>
If you eye what others do, and direct your courſe of Life accordingly, you do ſteer by a Planet, and not by the Pole-Star, and will never ſo come at the heavenly Harbour, the Port of Eternal bliſs and happineſs. I do not adviſe you againſt neceſſary Recrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for your health. But thoſe that ſpend much time in Playing, Carding, Dicing, or ſuch kind of Games (againſt which I hope I need not much caution you) do but nick-name it, when they call it Recreation, and are like ſuch, that have a nice ſtomach, who feed more on ſauce than they do on meat.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Make every day a working-day for Heaven, and every day a Sabbath from ſin; I mean a reſting-day from it. Be every day working out your Salvation with fear and trembling; your time is ſhort, and your work is great, and your Salvation lies at ſtake, therefore fall hard to your work; ſet on it with all your might, and hoard up all the time that poſſibly you can for it.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:63142:52"/>4. Remember often that Immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and Eternity hangs upon the ſpending of your time, and according as you ſpend this, ſo it will be with you to all eternity, either for happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or miſery. I have read a Story of a certain Gentlewoman, who uſed to ſpend much time in playing at Cards, and ſuch Games, coming once from that Paſtime late in the night, and finding her Waiting-Maid reading a good Book, caſt her Eyes over the Maids ſhoulder, and ſpake words to this effect; <hi>Thou poor melancholy Soul, what, alway reading and ſpending thy time in this manner? wilt thou take no comfort in thy life?</hi> But the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman being ſoon after got to Bed, could take no reſt, but lay groaning and ſighing bitterly. The Maid lying in the ſame Room, and hearing it, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to know the reaſon of it; to whom her Miſtreſs replied; <hi>I read this word</hi> Eternity <hi>in thy Book, which hath ſo pierced my heart, that I believe I ſhall never ſleep more till I have a better Aſſurance of my Eternity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:63142:53"/>Laſtly; Conſider ſeriouſly that you muſt at the great Day of the Lord, give an account for all your time. It's ſaid of <hi>Ignatius,</hi> that whenſoever he heard a Clock ſtrike, he would ſay, <hi>Here is now one hour more paſt, which I have to anſwer for.</hi> O what a heart-affecting conſideration is the loſs of time, with the account to be given for it? Holy Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> tells us, he familiarly knew a moſt holy, grave, and Reverend Divine, who was ſo affected with the words of a godly Woman, who at her death did often and vehemently cry out, <hi>O call time again! O call time again!</hi> that the ſenſe of it ſeemed to remain on his heart, and appear in his Praying, Preaching, and Converſation to his death: O that the reading of her words here might have the like hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Influence on your Heart and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation!</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:63142:53"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXII.</hi> Of the Order and Method of Duties every Week-day.</head>
               <p n="1">1. AS ſoon as you are awake in the morning, lift up your heart in ſome good thought to God. Let your heart be raiſed up in thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to God for the mercies of the former night, and by fiducial reliance on him for his Providence over you that day following. Set forth in the morning in the Name of God, reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to do all things that day in that Name; <hi>Col.</hi> 3.17. and for his Glory, and that you will ſo ſpend it for God. And likewiſe fortifie and arm your ſelf againſt all the temptations that you foreſee you are likely to meet with occaſionally that day. And if any thought about any worldly concern ſhall preſent it ſelf to you, ſtriving to get firſt in, check it with the words of our Saviour in another caſe; <hi>Touch me not, for I am not yet aſcended to my
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:63142:54"/>
Father.</hi> I have not yet raiſed up my heart to God. Thoughts will ſtand about your heart in a morning, as a company of Clients about the door, and that which firſt enters hath uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, moſt to do all that day. Satan will firſt croud in, if poſſible, by ſome worldly or vain thought, to get the firſt entrance in the morn; he is like a greedy and reſtleſs ſtomach-worm, that keeps a coyl to have his break-faſt before his Maſter be ſerved. Therefore let it be your diligent care as ſoon as you awake, to fill your heart with ſome thoughts of God, which will be the beſt break-faſt to keep out the wind of a temptation. And if you thus perfume the Soul in the morning with ſuch ſweet odours, you will the better keep out ill ſcents all the day. Let your heart be as the Sun-Dial, that early receives the Sun-beams, and goes along with it till the even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Let it receive the Beams of the Sun of Righteouſneſs freely in the morning, and he will ſhine on it all the day. If you do not at firſt ſet out
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:63142:54"/>
to a right point of the Compaſs, you will make a bad Voyage.</p>
               <div type="prayers">
                  <head>Ejaculations which may be uſed when you awake in or toward the Morning.</head>
                  <p>MY voice ſhalt thou hear in the morning, O Lord, in the morning will I direct my prayer unto thee, and will look up, <hi>Pſal. 5.3.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>How precious are thy thoughts unto me, O God? how great is the ſum of them? If I would count them, they are more in number than the Sand. When I awake I am ſtill with thee, <hi>Pſal. 139.17, 18.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>My Soul waiteth for the Lord, more than they that watch for the morning; I ſay, more than they that watch for the morning. <hi>Pſal. 130.6.</hi> O when ſhall the day dawn, and the day-ſtar ariſe in my heart?</p>
                  <p>It is of the Lords mercies that I am not conſumed, becauſe his compaſſions fail not; they are new every morning, <hi>Lam. 3.22, 23.</hi> Therefore my thanks ſhall never fail, but be new and freſh every morning alſo.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="96" facs="tcp:63142:55"/>
                     <hi>2. Let not your morning hours (which are the very flower and cream of time, the moſt precious of all the day for any work or duty) be ſpent in Bed, or vainly out of Bed. And while you are dreſſing, let ſome one (if you can conveniently) read to you, or elſe you may employ your time in thinking of the laſt Sermon you heard, or ſome other good thoughts, as of the Soul's Wedding Garment,</hi> Matth. <hi>22.11. or of the durable Cloathing,</hi> (Ezek. <hi>23.18.) in compariſon of which all the beſt Apparel is but a Cobweb Tiffany, a fine worthleſe Nothing; or you may uſe ſuch Ejaculations and Meditations as theſe following.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayers">
                  <head>Ejaculations and Meditations which may be uſed while you are dreſſing.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>P<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>T on the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and make no proviſion for the fleſh, to ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fil the luſts thereof,</hi> Rom. 13. <hi>ult.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Put on the New Man, which after God is created in righteouſneſs and true holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> Eph. 4.24.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="97" facs="tcp:63142:55"/>
                     <hi>Be you cloathed with humility, fo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> God reſiſteth the proud, and giveth grace to the humble;</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.5.</p>
                  <p>This Garment is very neat, but how much more comely and glorious is the Wedding Garment of Souls, the Robe of Chriſt's Righteouſneſs, which is put on by Faith!</p>
                  <p>Oh what a bleſſed time will that be when I ſhall be arrayed with the perfect beauty of Holineſs, with the white Garments of perfect Light and Glory! then ſhall be the Marriage of the Lamb.</p>
                  <p>Am I not now garniſhing a Body which may in a few days turn to rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenneſs? O what ſhall this vile Body be deckt, as a dead Body, ſtuck with flowers, and the precious Soul, be neglected!</p>
                  <p n="3">3. When you have got your cloaths on, then ſolemnly retire into your Cloſet for Devotion, if no other ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary buſineſs call you unto ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe before, which may often happen when you have a Family; which when you have, then, if occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:63142:56"/>
be, firſt ſettle affairs therein, for the fore-noon work, and then having ſounded a retreat in your heart to temporal affairs, you may after retire into your Cloſet with more freedom from domeſtick cares, and without fear of interruption; whereas if you went to your private Devotion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, you would be forced to cut it ſhorter, to curt and clip that duty.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Manage your domeſtick affairs with prudence and diligence, but not with ſollicitous eagerneſs and vexing care. <hi>Solomon</hi>'s virtuous Woman, looketh well to the affairs of her houſhold<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and eateth not the bread of idleneſs; <hi>Prov.</hi> 31.27. <hi>A wiſe woman buildeth her houſe, Prov.</hi> 14.2. ſhe ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies in every buſineſs how to ſet eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing in order, as the Carpenter ſtudies how to ſet every part of the frame in joynt. But yet herein be not like <hi>Martha,</hi> while ſhe played the good huſwife, cumbred about many things. And if many things fall out together, diſpatch them in a prudent order, and not with too much haſte
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:63142:56"/>
and eagerneſs. Thoſe things are ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom well done, that are done over-haſtily. The Drones flie about more haſtily than the Bees, but they make no Honey but Combs only.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. At your meals reflect upon God, turn your eyes to ſee his mercies to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards you. Thus will you enjoy God in all. A carnal heart regards no more than the bare enjoyment of theſe out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward mercies, but looks not to the ſpring from whence they come, as a gracious heart doth, who finds the greateſt ſweetneſs of them, to be their coming from the Love of God. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, you may then reflect on God by raiſing up your thoughts to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights in him; think ſeriouſly in your heart, if this meat be ſo ſweet to my taſt, how much more ſweet is Chriſt and hidden Mannah? Here you may take occaſion, like him that ſate at meat with Chriſt, <hi>Luk.</hi> 14.15. to raiſe up your thoughts to the bleſſedneſs of him that ſhall eat bread in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God. Thus you will feaſt your Soul, while you are feeding your
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:63142:57"/>
Body. Thus you may ſo ſweeten your Meat, and ſpice your Cup, with the relliſhes of the Love of God, as may make your Table better, and more pleaſant to you, than the Tables of the greateſt Ladies in the World.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. In the midſt of all your dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick over-ſight of affairs (when you ſhall have any) eye Gods Providence, caſting all your care upon him, and ſo he will bleſs your endeavours. And often retire to God by Ejaculations, ſhort Addreſſes, and holy Breathings of Soul after him. By theſe you may ſanctifie both your walking, riding and journeying (which are uſually vainly ſpent in multitudes of idle thoughts that ſignifie nothing) and all your affairs alſo whatſoever. This was <hi>Nehemiah</hi>'s practice when he was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the King, he then prayed to the God of Heaven, <hi>Chap.</hi> 2.4. I do not believe that he then went into ſome place by himſelf to pray; no, he ſent up only ſome ſhort Ejaculations to God, while he was in the King's pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence. It's reported of holy Mr. <hi>Dod,</hi>
                     <pb n="101" facs="tcp:63142:57"/>
that he never got up upon his Horſe, but he prayed before he alighted off. In every corner there is a Throne of Grace, therefore often, every day, improve this priviledge; be often looking up to God, and caſting your eyes to Heaven; and ſo you may bring down Heaven to you. As often as you want direction in any ſudden caſe and affair, or relief in any need, by one lift or ſudden glance of the Eye of Faith to Jeſus Chriſt, you may have it. And in ſuch caſes you may uſe as an Ejaculatory Prayer that of honourable <hi>Jabez; O that thou wouldſt bleſs me indeed! and that thy hand may be with me! and that thou wouldſt keep me from evil, that it may not grieve me!</hi> 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 4.10. which was ſo pleaſing to God, that it's added there, and God granted him that which he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſted.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Beſides thoſe ſhort Ejaculations now mentioned, you muſt make ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Addreſſes to God twice a day at leaſt. The Soul muſt have her ſet meals, or a ſet ſervice to God twice
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:63142:58"/>
every day at leaſt. Twice every day the Clock muſt neceſſarily be wound up. <hi>Aaron</hi> lighted the Lamps, and burned Incenſe evening and morning; <hi>Exod.</hi> 30.7, 8. Reading of Scripture is to us as his burning the Lamps, and praying is as his burning Incenſe; theſe two muſt go both together, like eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and drinking. If you do ſolemnly addreſs your ſelf to God in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, you ſhall be in a better frame and temper of heart all the day after: and if you do it at night, you will find a better appetite to it again next morning. But I do not limit you to twice a day; it will be beſt to do it as often as with any conveniency you can. Holy <hi>David</hi> did it thrice a day, evening and morning, and at noon; <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55.17. ſo did <hi>Daniel, ch.</hi> 6. <hi>v.</hi> 10.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Fill up all the intervals and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cancies of your time every day, thoſe Parentheſes or breathing times be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt one employment and another, with reading ſome good and profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Books, neceſſary Recreations for your health, charitable Viſits of
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:63142:58"/>
the Poor, friendly Courteſies, neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourly Civilities, or ſome profitable Diſcourſe, or Recourſes to God in Prayer, beſide your evening and morning Addreſſes.</p>
                  <p n="9">9 Every night before you go to Bed, retire your ſelf, and call your ſelf ſeriouſly to an account in an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial ſurvey of all the remarkable actions, and alſo of the mercies of the paſt day. And for your better di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection therein, you may ask your ſelf theſe following queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. What time have I loſt or trifled away this day?</p>
                  <p n="2">2. What particular duties have I omitted?</p>
                  <p n="3">3. What ſins have I committed this day?</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Out of what principle have I performed my duties? whether out of an inward byaſs of Love to God, or from ſome outward Poiſes and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives? Have not the wheels been oiled by ſome ſiniſter oreſpects in duty? Hath not my perf<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rmance of
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:63142:59"/>
duties been more out of cuſtom, or to ſtop the mouth of natural Conſcience, than out of any delight in them?</p>
                  <p n="5">5. In this account ask your ſelf what have my Receivings been from God this day? what Talents and Mercies have I had from him? and how have I laid them out for him? what Mercies have I received, and what returns have I made for them?</p>
                  <p n="10">10. Cloſe your eyes at night with ſome thoughts of God and Chriſt. When you are compoſing your ſelf to ſleep, commit your ſelf then both Body and Soul into his hands to keep them for you, while you ſleep, as the Child when it goes to Bed gives its Mother what it would have kept ſafely. Or going to Bed, you may ſuitably meditate on Death, whoſe Image and Picture Sleep is. Look upon your Bed as upon your Grave; think to die as often as you fall aſleep. Sleep is a ſhort Death, and Death is nothing elſe but a long ſleep: the Bed is a grave for one night, and the grave is a Bed for many Ages. We
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:63142:59"/>
expect to awaken from our Beds, and we hope to riſe again from our graves. If you ſeriouſly follow this courſe every night, you will have Jeſus Chriſt lie all night, as a bundle of Myrrh betwixt your breaſts, and will find your heart in a good frame when you awake. If you thus rake up the fire over night, you will find it in in the morning. <hi>Solomon</hi>'s virtuous Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man lets not her Candle go out by night; <hi>Prov.</hi> 31.18. Let your Lamp be well trimm'd, your Grace well lighted and put in exerciſe when you compoſe your ſelf to reſt; and like a good Watch-candle, you will find it burning when you awake. O how many are there that lie down as the Beaſts in their Straw, without ſo much as bidding their Souls good night?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayers">
                  <head>Ejaculations which may be uſed at night before ſleep.</head>
                  <p>I <hi>Will both lay me down and ſleep, for thou Lord make ſtme dwell in ſafety;</hi> Pſal. 4.8.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="106" facs="tcp:63142:60"/>
                     <hi>When thou lieſt down thou ſhalt not be afraid, yea thou ſhalt lie down, and thy ſleep ſhall be ſweet; Prov.</hi> 3.24.</p>
                  <p>Lord, I commit my ſelf both Body and Soul into thy hands, who art the keeper of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and neither ſlumbers nor ſleeps. <hi>The Lord is my keeper, the Lord is my defence, who neither ſlum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers nor ſleeps; Pſal.</hi> 21.4, 5.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. If there be any interceptions, any interruptions or breaches of ſleep in the night, fill up thoſe vacancies with meditations on ſome Sermon lately heard, or on what you read the day before in the Bible, or ſome other good Book, or elſe with ſome Parenthetical Ejaculations, as devout Souls, thoſe ſpiritual Crickets of the night have uſed to do.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayers">
                  <head>Ejaculations that may be uſed in the Night in breaches of ſleep.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>BY night upon my bed, I ſought him whom my Soul loveth; Cant.</hi> 3.1. O let me not have occaſion to ſay, <hi>I ſought him, but I found him not;</hi> or to go about as the Spouſe there did, in a
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:63142:60"/>
dark night of deſertion, crying out like a deſolate Widdow, <hi>Saw ye him whom my Soul loveth?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>With my Soul have I deſired thee in the night; yea with my ſpirit within me will I ſeek thee early;</hi> Iſa. 26.9. <hi>My Soul ſhall be ſatisfied as with marrow and fatneſs, and my mouth ſhall praiſe thee with joyful lips, while I remember thee on my bed, and meditate on thee in the night watches;</hi> Pſal. 63.5, 6.</p>
                  <p>O when ſhall I come and appear in the preſence of God, in the City of the New <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> which hath no need of the Sun, neither of the Moon to ſhine in it, for the glory of God doth lighten it, and tke Lamb is the light thereof: And there ſhall be no Night there, and they need no Candle, neither Light of the Sun, for the Lord God giveth them Light, and they ſhall reign for ever and ever; <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.23.</p>
                  <p>O when ſhall my Soul be received into the number of that heavenly Chore that ſing for ever <hi>Hallelujahs,</hi> that reſt not day and night, ſaying,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:63142:61"/>
Holy, holy, holy, Lord God, Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which was, and is, and is to come; <hi>Rev.</hi> 4.8.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I will bleſs the Lord who hath given me counſel, my reins alſo</hi> (my inward thoughts) <hi>inſtruct me in the night ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; Pſal.</hi> 16.7.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXIII.</hi> How to ſpend the Lord's Day.</head>
               <p>IN general, Be a curious ſpender of your time on the Lord's Day. This will be a holy curioſity. Let this day be your delight, ſpend it wholly in walking in the Spouſes Garden a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Duties and Ordinances, with a ſweet and holy pleaſure, where there is ſo great variety, that you may go (like a diligent Bee) from one Flower to another, from one Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to another, and never take ſurfeit. It's the whole day that God commans to be ſanctified, and therefore the whole muſt be ſpent in holy exerciſes. Therefore do not think it ſufficient for the ſanctification thereof, that you
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:63142:61"/>
have been at the Publick Worſhip in the Aſſembly, unleſs the whole day were ſpent there, as was antiently done by the Primitive Chriſtians in their Publick Aſſemblies, almoſt from morning to night. On other days of the week Duties call for time, but time calls for Duties on the Lord's Day. If I were to paſs my Judgment on the Religion of any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, I would take my meaſures from the manner of their obſervation or the Lord's Day.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Before you go to the Publick Worſhip, ſpend what time you can in private (beſide Duty in the Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) that ſo you may be better pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for the Publick: for private Devotion before will be a great means to prevent worldly thoughts and diſtractions, when you are in the Aſſembly. Worldly thoughts and cares do play the part of little Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, if they cannot keep the Mother from going abroad, they will cry to go along with her; and theſe, if they cannot keep you from Church, they
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:63142:62"/>
will ſtrive to go thither with you; but ſolemn preparation before, lays a reſtraint on them, gives them a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge, to prevent and hinder their accompanying of you.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Be a conſtant, diligent, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verent Attendant on the Publick Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, and make the beſt improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of them for your Soul. This is a frequenting the Royal Exchange of Chriſtians, and would exceedingly tend to the Souls advantage. Chriſt's preſence is moſt to be found in the Publick Ordinances: he walks in the midſt of the golden Candleſticks: here the whole Aſſembly with united and concentricated Forces do beſiege the Throne of Grace; and ſo their prayers have more power with God. Muſick in Conſort is the moſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant. That is the ſweeteſt Poſie that is made of moſt Flowers. The prayers of many ſmell ſweeteſt with God. Beſides, Affections are more wrought on in publick than in private (which ſome great Naturaliſts have obſerved as one of Natures great Myſteries)
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:63142:62"/>
and where Affections are moſt raiſed, there God uſually confers the greater bleſſing. Indeed ſometimes it falls out that Chriſtians are more dull un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the publick means, which may be in Judgment, when they either put too much confidence in ſuch pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, or are fallen to a loathing or ſlighting of that ſpiritual food, either becauſe they have it ſo oft, or by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of ſome circumſtances in Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, which they like not.</p>
               <p n="4">4. When you come home from the Publick, be careful to ſpend your time in Religious Exerciſes. Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate on what you have heard, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, like a diligent Bee, gathered abroad in the Publick Aſſembly, the ſweet of heavenly Flowers, work your Honey-comb within your own Hive. Digeſt well by private Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation that ſpiritual meat, which was ſet before you in the Diſhes of the Publick Ordinances. Meditate alſo on the Attributes of God, the Works of God, and eſpecially the Mercies of God, that you may be ſtirred up
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:63142:63"/>
to holy rejoycings, praiſes, and thankſgivings, which are the moſt proper work of the day, which is a day of thankſgiving, and commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Mercies of God, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of the Reſurrection of Chriſt, and the great work of Redemption.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Be careful that your Servants do not prophane or miſ-ſpend this day, as being tender of their Souls, as well as your own. <hi>Solomon</hi>'s virtuous Woman gave a portion of holy In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, as well as of Food, to her Servants and Maidens; <hi>Prov</hi> 31.15, 26.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXIV.</hi> Of Holy Duties in general.</head>
               <p n="1">1. BEfore you go to any Duty ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs your ſelf to Jeſus Chriſt for a ſupply of grace, for the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance thereof. If you be to go to a new act of praying, or hearing, or receiving the Sacraments, you muſt eye Jeſus Chriſt again, put forth a new act of Faith towards him, and
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:63142:63"/>
labour for new Influences, and a freſh ſupply of Spirit from him.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Do not only number your Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, but weigh your Duties, how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; how many look only how oft they go to Duties, but never ſeriouſly how, or in what manner they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form them? and ſo cheat themſelves everlaſtingly, concluding themſelves to be in a ſtate of Grace, becauſe of their conſtancy in Duties, but miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carry everlaſtingly for want of a right manner of performing them, as out of a right ſpring and principle, and to a right end, and with ſincerity and fervency of affection. Though the Tree bear many large and fair fruits, yet it is not much valued, unleſs they have a good relliſh. If the fruits that your Soul brings forth have not a good taſt, through the ſincerity and right ends thereof, or taſt not of the Love of God, they will not be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable unto God. Let all your works be done in Love; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.14.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Do not only perform holy du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, but love holy duties, ſo they will
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:63142:64"/>
be more acceptable to the God of Love. An ungodly Man or Woman may often go to prayer, but they love it not; they may hear the Word, but they receive not the Truth in the love of it: But a good heart loves duties. So long as you cannot find any relliſh in Ordinances or private Duties, but are in an indifferency whether you perform them or no, or have your frequent intermiſſions of theſe meals, ſo that ſometimes you take them, and ſometimes you let them alone, it is a ſign you are not ſound within; or if you do conſtantly take them, if it be without an appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite, and perform holy duties, only to ſtop the mouth of Conſcience, its an argument your Soul is not in health. Till you find ſweetneſs in Ordinances, the caſe is not well with you, as it ſhould be, the Soul is out of frame. If once you love duties, they will be a delight and refreſhment to you. All the ways of Chriſt are Beds of Spices and Roſes, and can you walk on ſuch, and not be requited for it
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:63142:64"/>
with ſweet and fragrant ſmells? Thoſe that carry bundles of Spices from <hi>Arabia,</hi> have their Spirits refreſht with the ſweet Odours that breathe from them. A good Chriſtian is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſht in duty; the Soul can ſing at her work. Love turns all pains into pleaſures. Though the Mother take a great deal of pains in tending the Child, yet ſhe finds a ſweet delight in it, becauſe of her love to it. A good Chriſtian can ſay with <hi>David, O how I love thy Law! Pſal.</hi> 119.97. And, <hi>I delight to do thy Will, O my God! Pſal.</hi> 40.8.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXV.</hi> Of Prayer.</head>
               <p n="1">1. DO not ruſh on Prayer pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently, without ſome ſerious conſideration before. Read there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſome portion of Scripture before you pray. This will afford you mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of meditation, which will furniſh you with matter for Prayer; for ſo
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:63142:65"/>
you may turn what you have read in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Prayer. A good Heart is by one Duty quickned, and prepared for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as the Wild Bores, by whetting their Tusks with their other Teeth, make them ſharp, and ſo every Tooth mutually ſets an edge on another. If therefore you be to read, Pray before by ſome ſhort Addreſs to God, if to Pray, read before; Yea, Pray alſo before Prayer, that God would Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt you in Prayer, and deliver you from the Evil Infirmities of your Prayer. Holy <hi>David</hi> Prays for his own Prayers, <hi>Pſal</hi> 141.1, 2.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Look not upon Prayer as a task, but as a priviledge: O! what a great and glorious priviledge is it, that the pooreſt Saint may with boldneſs have acceſs to God! <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.18 <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.1, 2. Is it not a Royal Priviledge to have a Key in our keeping, that opens Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Gates, and lets into the Preſence Chamber of the King of Glory? To ſpeak with him at any time? If you would thus look upon it, I ſhould not need to perſwade you to go to
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:63142:65"/>
Prayer conſtantly, Morning and Even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing This would be in ſtead of a hundred Arguments, that Prayer is ſo High and ſo Royal a Priviledge, that you may thereby go boldly to the Throne of Grace, draw near to God himſelf, and lay your Petition in his Boſom, and plead your Cauſe before him, and fill your Mouth with Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, and Reaſon out your great Concernments with him, and receive his Anſwers.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Pray Earneſtly. Lazy Devotion and Key-cold Prayers will never pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail. You muſt wreſtle with God in Prayer, like Holy <hi>Jacob,</hi> that you may prevail. In wreſtling one ſingle Perſon ſtrives with another, ſo the Devout Soul with God; they go to it ſingly, as it were Hand to Hand, and have as it were a ſingle Combat in private. The Devout Saint loves to wreſtle with God in the Cloſet, when no Body is preſent, the Door being ſhut, he loves not to have Spectators of it, he then comes up cloſe to God, and gets within him, takes hold of
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:63142:66"/>
his Everlaſting Arms. Thus the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of <hi>Canaan</hi> Wreſtled with Chriſt, ſhe ſtands to it, though ſhe had ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Repulſes from him. The Soul thus Wreſtles with God, as a Child with the Father, who is much delighted and pleaſed, to let it get the better on him, to encourage it, and after takes it up from its Knees into his Arms, when you go to Prayer, you muſt ſet all your faculties on work, you muſt open and ſpread the Sails, open and ſpread forth your Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as wide as you can, that they may gather wind enough, to waft you over to the Land of Promiſe.</p>
               <p n="4">4. See that your Prayers be follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Diligent and Serious Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, for effecting of that which you have Prayed for, otherwiſe they will be Fruitleſs. If you pray for Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and never take pains by Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Study to get it, or for the Mortification of Sin, and never La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to Subdue and Kill it, or for Reformation of your Life, and never ſet about the Reforming of it, your
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:63142:66"/>
Prayers will be to little purpoſe. It's as if a Man ſhould pray to be Cured of a Diſeaſe, and yet never uſe Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, nor Dyet or Exerciſe to Cure it: Or like ſuch, as the Greek Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Orator ſpeaks of, who ſeeing great Hailſtones falling down on their Heads, Prayed to be ſecured from them, but would not ſtir a foot. Gods uſual way is, to give in Bleſſings to us concurring with him in the uſe of means, and he will not vary from his Ordinary Method, unleſs upon moſt ſpecial Occaſions.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Look after your Prayers, to ſee what becomes of them, and what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns, what Anſwer you have of them. Thus did <hi>David, Pſ.</hi> 5.3. and 58.8. <hi>Habackuck</hi> having Prayed, ſtands upon his watch, ſets himſelf on his Tower, to ſee what God would ſay to him. There are many times ſuch Diſpenſations of God towards us, which we might ſee, did Ecchoe to our Prayers, if we did well obſerve them. Do not then ſhoot out your Prayers, as Children do their Arrows,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:63142:67"/>
who ſhoot them away, and never look after them more: But rather as Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers that ſhoot them up into the Air, and ſtand ſtill waiting for their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down again.</p>
               <p n="6">6. In all your Prayers, let Prayers be mixt, and have a good ſhare, and due proportion in them. Do not ſhuffle up Praeiſs into a Corner of your Prayers, do not croud nor hud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle them up into a ſcant and narrow Compaſs, as moſt do, or thruſt them into the very End and Concluſion of your Prayers: But let them bear a part throughout the whole Duty.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAAP. XXVI.</hi> Of Deſiring the Sincere Milk of the Word.</head>
               <p>AS a New-Born Babe deſire the Sincere Milk of the Word, that you may grow thereby. The Word is as Milk, go then to it as Children to the Breaſt, with an Appetite, but be ſure it be Milk that you deſire, and
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:63142:67"/>
not Froth, Power and Virtue, not the Froth of empty words of Rhetorick, which are not to be accounted as Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Milk, it's plain ſong always that makes the beſt Muſick. Deſire that Milk alway which is moſt wholſom, not that which is moſt luſcious, and beſt pleaſes a dainty or curious Pallat.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Do not ſatisfie your ſelf with ſome weak Velleities and faint wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, or whimperings after the Breaſts of the Word, but let your deſires af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this ſincere Milk, be ſtrong and earneſt, accompanyed with Diligent Endeavours after it, and ſuck the Breaſts well, that you may have it, deſire it by the effectual fervent Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Faith. This is indeed that real and ſpiritual ſucking, which is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of Newborn Babes in Chriſt. The Prayer of Faith is the Mouth, or the two Lips, whereby we ſuck Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Milk, and draw in Heavenly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluences, and Divine Sweetneſs from the Word. <hi>Ask and ye ſhall have, Math.</hi> 7.7, 8. but then this asking muſt be in Faith. The Mother opens the
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:63142:68"/>
Breaſt when the Child Cryes after it. If you thirſt after this Heavenly Milk of the Word, God will give it, his Spirit will Communicate ſweet In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flows to your Soul; he ſometimes lays Wormwood to the Breaſts of Providence, to wean us from Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-Comforts, but he would never have us wean'd from the Milk of the Word, while we are in this Life, but would have us lye continually at the Breaſt of the two Teſtaments. Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren while they are in health, are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt continually Sucking, and never ſatisfied, but while they are at the Breaſt. If your Soul be in a good healthy Condition, you will not be well ſatisfied, but while you are lying at the Dugs of Ordinances, at theſe Spiritual Milk-pales, as <hi>Job</hi> calls the Breaſts.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If after you have lyen long at the Breaſts, waited long at the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, you find nothing come, no Inflows, no virtue, no refreſhments or comfort from them, ſo that they ſeem to be dry Breaſts, yet give them not
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:63142:68"/>
over, as ſome are too apt to do, think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it in vain to wait any longer, when as the fault is in themſelves, not in the Word and Ordinances, they are full Breaſts, but theſe poor Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures cannot act faith to draw. God may ſee cauſe ſometime to with-hold this Spiritual Milk, to withdraw his influences, and put forth no virtue or efficacy in the Word, yet do not give over waiting; continue ſtill in the diligent uſe of the means of Grace, he will pleaſe to let down this Milk in the end; what you do not find at one time, you may at another; he will at length ſmile on you in the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, and let you have Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical Fruitions. If you did live much by Faith, you would find theſe full Breaſts flow plentifully.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Think that while you are in this World, you will have need of this Milk of the Word, need of Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. There are ſome fond Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, that think they are above Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, which are only for Babes and Punies, that they are paſt the Milk
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:63142:69"/>
of the Word, and are grown too old to ſuck the breaſts. I wiſh they were ever new-born Babes in Chriſt, which is to be feared they never were, tho' they conceit themſelves to be tall and perfect Men and Women in Chriſt. I have read of one <hi>Philinus,</hi> that never fed of any other meat or drink all his life but only Milk. All the true Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God, muſt certainly while they live here, feed on no other food but only Scripture-milk. God will not nouriſh our Souls by immediate influences, and communications from himſelf, till we come to the heavenly Land, that flows with Milk and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and to ſit at God's own Table at the Supper of the Lamb in the Kingdom of Glory. When the new-born Babes are grown to a perfect ſtature, and are perfectly wean'd from the World, which will not be till this Mortal ſhall have put on Immortality; then, and not till then ſhall we have imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate communion with God, which is the very ſweet of Heaven. The Pot of Manna muſt continue in the
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:63142:69"/>
Ark of the Church, till we come to the Celeſtial <hi>Canaan.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. The end of deſiring this Milk, muſt be that you may grow thereby. We are nouriſht and made to grow by the ſame things whereby we were firſt bred. The Milk by which the Infant is nouriſht, is but the blood of which it was framed in the womb, further concocted in the breaſts, and turn'd white there. So it is only the ſame Word by which we were ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually begot, that doth cauſe us ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually to grow: For indeed all the Ordinances, which are the Souls nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment, are nothing elſe but the Word it ſelf in ſeveral forms, or the ſubject matter of the Word. The Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the Lords Supper, which was ſpecially appointed for the Souls nouriſhment, and growth in grace, is but the Word in a more ſenſible form, or as the ſame meat otherwiſe dreſt and cookt, to make another Diſh. The Sacrament is but the Word viſibly prepared to the Eye, by an exuberance of mercy, which
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:63142:70"/>
was barely ſet forth to the Ear in Reading and Preaching, that our Eye might affect our Heart, and the whole Man might be fed with more apt and ſuitable congruity, by ſuch viſible ſigns. If you be new born, you muſt not ſatisfie your ſelf with that, but you muſt further look to it, that you grow up in Chriſt. It is a ſhrowd ſign, that that perſon is not in Chriſt, who is well contented with preſent grace, without endeavouring after growth therein. Be not like <hi>Luther</hi>'s Changeling, ever ſucking, never thri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving. Try then whether you grow in Holineſs. Do you perform duties with more heart and life than for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly? Are you now, not only for perſonal Holineſs, but Relation Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXVII.</hi> Of Reading the Word.</head>
               <p>REad every day ſome portion of Scripture either out of the Old or New Teſtament, but eſpecially out
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:63142:70"/>
of the New: Make uſe of both theſe Breaſts for your ſpiritual nouriſhment; prize both Law and Goſpel; highly va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue and ſtudy both. The Child likes to lie ſometimes at the one breaſt, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times at the other; but yet the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel is the better breaſt, and Faith loves moſt to lie thereat; it finds moſt ſweetneſs in the Goſpel Honey-comb; it gets Honey in every little Cell of it, taſts ſweetneſs in every word or tittle of the Goſpel.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Read the Scripture underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly; ſee when you read that you underſtand the ſubſtance and ſenſe, the drift and ſcope of the H. Ghoſt in that Scripture which you read, otherwiſe you read unprofitably. I ſpeak now of thoſe places of Scripture which contain either ſome Article of Faith, or matters of practical Godlineſs, ſuch as are incumbent upon Chriſtians, to learn to obſerve and practiſe. But as for thoſe places that contain meer ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culative and controverſial matter, or hard queſtionable Points in Divinity, an ordinary Chriſtian need not be cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:63142:71"/>
for a diſtinct underſtanding of them.</p>
               <p n="3">3. When you begin to read any portion of Scripture, pray unto God, that he would enlighten you by his Spirit, that you may underſtand it, and read it with reverence as the Word of the moſt holy God; and when any thing affects you, pray to God, that he would work that parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular paſſage on your heart before you read any further.</p>
               <p n="4">4. In reading take ſpecial notice of, and mark thoſe places of Scripture, which you find moſt ſuitable and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficial to you, and read them over oftner than others. Let your heart, like a diligent Bee, ſit longeſt on thoſe Flowers that will afford you moſt Honey; and yet if you ſtay thereon as long as you can, you ſhall never get out all the ſweetneſs, you may afterwards return to read again and find more; and though the Soul have even laded her ſelf, ſhe leaves them, as the Bee her Flowers, as whole as ſhe found them. A good ſerious
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:63142:71"/>
Chriſtian may perhaps have read a Chapter twenty times over before, yet afterwards in the reading of it, God may diſcover ſomething to him a new, ſo that he then gathers that thence, which he never did before, and taſts a new and freſh ſweetneſs there.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Read the Scriptures with this end and intent, that you may know what God would have you to do, and what he would have you forbear, that the word of God may dwell in you richly in all Wiſdom (as the Apoſtle ſpeaks, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.16.) <hi>i. e.</hi> that you may be ſo wiſe as know to apply it, to know how to uſe ſuch an Example, and ſuch a reproof. It's the Wiſdom of a Tradeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, to know how to uſe ſuch a Tool, ſuch an Inſtrument or Engin, and of a Chriſtian to know how to uſe ſuch a portion of Scripture, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what Chriſt did in ſuch a Temptation, what <hi>Abraham, David</hi> and <hi>Job,</hi> did in ſuch a Caſe. Look in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Word of God, as into an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Glaſs, whereby to know how
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:63142:72"/>
to dreſs your ſelf, Look into it, that you may ſee all your ſpots, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is amiſs, and out of order, that you may amend and redreſs the ſame, yea, that you may behold in this Glaſs, the Glory of the Lord, and be chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged into the ſame Image, as from Glory to Glory, <hi>i. e.</hi> into the Beauty of Holineſs, which this Glaſs is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.18.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXVIII.</hi> Of Hearing the Word Profitably.</head>
               <p>VVHen the Word is Preached, do not ſtay at home, no not to read good Books. They are ſtrange Children, that when the Nurſe holds out the Breaſt, will cry out for the Sucking-Bottle. God is pleaſed to put forth his Spirit in the Preaching of the Word, more effectually than in the reading it. The ſame Milk is more Effectual and Nouriſhing, when it is taken warm immediately from the Breaſt, than when it hath been
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:63142:72"/>
Milkt out, and ſtood a while, and when it can be had, you make no uſe of the Bottle or Spoon. Though a Printed Sermon be as good, as that which is heard from the Miniſters Mouth, yet it hath not pleaſed God ordinarily to work Converſion by Printed Sermons at ſuch times, when the Word might be heard Preached. Though <hi>Abana</hi> and <hi>Pharpar</hi> had as good water as <hi>Jordan,</hi> yet it would not heal <hi>Naamans</hi> Leproſie. That Honey taſts ſweeteſt, which is ſuckt imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately out of the Comb, and much better than that which is eaten out of a Diſh, and that Word is ſweeter to the Souls Pallat, which drops imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately from the Miniſters Mouth, and came directly from his Heart thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, than that which is read out of a Book. That which comes warm from the Heart of the Preacher, is moſt likely to go to the Heart of the Hearer. That perſon which will not go to hear the word Preached, but will rather ſtay at home to Read is like a ſullen Child, that will not eat
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:63142:73"/>
his Meat, unleſs he himſelf may cut it. You may expect that God will give a Bleſſing to the endeavours of his Faithful, Laborious Miniſters. We uſe to feed our Nurſes well, that our Children may fare the better.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Mark the Doctrine, Deſign, and Drift of the Preacher all along, that you may underſtand the Sermon, and obſerve his Method, that you may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member it. For ſo it will be the more portable for the memory.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Go not to hear the word with a common frame of Heart, or with the ſame end, that you go to hear another kind of Diſcourſe: But go, that you may be made Holy, otherwiſe you go not to the Word, as a New-born Babe, with an Appetite to the Milk of it. You muſt come to theſe Golden Pipes, <hi>Zach.</hi> 4.2. that they may empty Golden Oyl into you, or they will do you no good. <hi>Canaan</hi> it ſelf, that flows with Milk and Honey, would be but a Deſert, a Hony-Comb with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Honey, meer Wax, if Chriſt were not there. Therefore go to the Word,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:63142:73"/>
to find ſomething of Chriſt there, to get ſome influences from him, and not barely to hear a Man ſpeak, go to hear not ſo much that you may know more but that you may be affected more.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Hear the Word attentively and diligently, becauſe it is your Life, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.46. The things ſpoken, do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern the Soul, and are moſt Momen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous; how ſlightly and careleſly do multitudes of People hear the word Preached, as if it were a matter of ſmall concern? Which might juſtly cauſe God to take away the word from us; when the Mother ſees that the Child doth but play with the Breaſts, ſhe puts them up.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Labour to be affected with the word. I mean not with ſome elegant Expreſſions, or pleaſing Compariſons that are brought in a Sermon to tickle the fancy of a Delicate Hearer. If theſe only affect you, you get no good, but ſuck wind rather than Nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. The Bee lights not on the Roſe, which hath the freſheſt Colour, and ſweeteſt Smell, but on the Thyme,
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:63142:74"/>
which is an Herb of little beauty. A Devout Soul reſts not on Truths cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly deckt with Eloquence, but upon plain naked Truths, to fetch Honey from. It likes the moſt ſaving, weighty and powerful Truths, the Spiritualneſs of the matter, the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs of Soul-Searching Doctrines, ſuch Doctrines as beat down Luſt and Corruption. But a formaliſt is only delighted with the Hiſtory, the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance of Language, the quaint Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or the Rational Evidence of the Diſcourſe, and ſo reſts in the outward ſhell, and taſts not the Kernell. If theſe things only do affect you in hearing, you did never yet real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taſt the goodneſs of Sermon-Milk, or the ſweetneſs and pretiouſneſs of Chriſt in a Sermon, which if once you had taſted, how would your Heart be affected and raviſht with it? It's only the taſting of the Hony-Comb, that makes one affected with it, and to long after more.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Ponder upon what you hear, lay it up in your Heart, ſo as to retain it.
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:63142:74"/>
Thus did <hi>Mary</hi> by Chriſts ſayings, ſhe kept them all, and pondered them in her Heart, <hi>Luke</hi> 2.19. The word is a Jewel, lock it up in the Cabinet of your Heart. It's pondering on the word in the Heart, that doth make it Nouriſhment to you by Digeſting of it, and turning it into the Blood and Spirits of Holineſs. This is the Squee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing of the Hony-Comb of the word into the Heart, which makes it yield abundant ſtore of refreſhing ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Yea, and preſſeth it ſo, that it ſlides down deep into the Heart, ſo as it is made to abide there. When the Miniſter hath laid on a healing plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, Meditation binds it faſt on, makes it ſtick, and abide, which otherwiſe would rub off again preſently, without doing any good, it faſtens on our Hearts the truths which we have heard.</p>
               <p n="7">7. If you would profit by the word preached, then pray for the Miniſter before you go to Church. <hi>Col.</hi> 4.3. <hi>Eph</hi> 6 19. Pray to God to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect him to ſpeak a word in Seaſon to you, that might be ſuitable to
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:63142:75"/>
your Condition, and work upon your Heart. I am perſwaded that one rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why People reap no more benefit by the word, is becauſe they do not before pray for the Miniſter, or for a Bleſſing on the word, that he ſhall preach to them. Conſider that thus praying for him, you pray for your ſelf, if the Mother have a full Breaſt, it is the benefit of the Child. St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi> praiſed God for furniſhing his Nurſe with Milk, when he had pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed without it. O pray to God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly before you go to Church, that he would enable the Miniſter to do the work of a Spiritual Nurſe well, and then you will find that you will have matter to praiſe God for the good, that you ſhall reap after by his Church Nurſery.</p>
               <p n="8">8. When you come home, retire your ſelf a little, and repeat over to your ſelf, the moſt practical truths which you have heard, make Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of them to your ſelf, and preſs them home upon your own Heart. Think not how the Doctrine you have
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:63142:75"/>
heard, doth fit others, this hinders your profiting by the word, but think how it fits your ſelf.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXIX.</hi> Of Receiving the Sacrament of the Lords Supper.</head>
               <p n="1">1. NEglect no opportunity of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a gueſt at this Sacred Feaſt of the Lords Supper, and take care that in all your Approaches to it, you come worthily. This would be a prime and moſt Soveraign means to your living well, which is the deſign of all the Advice that I have given you. O what Excellent and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Lives did the Primitive Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians lead, while they received the Sacrament every day, or every Lords Day? They were thereby inflamed with ſuch Zeal and Holy Courage, that they were ſaid to come from the Sacrament, like Lyons breathing fire, and hence in <hi>Cyprians</hi> time, they had it every day, that they might be the
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:63142:76"/>
more animated to lay out their Blood for Chriſt. This Sacrament, ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> is for the Noble Eagles that would have their thoughts on high; it helps Souls mightily to mount up with wings as Eagles, to run and not be weary, to fly ſwiftly through dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties and duties, and to make them aſcend up in a fiery Chariot of Love. Chriſtians may hereby be brought unto, and preſerved in a Holy Galan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try of Spirit, and briskneſs and live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs in well doing, and to move as in the Chariots of <hi>Aminadab,</hi> with nimble vigor. The Elixir of Chriſts Blood in the Sacrament, will make the believer full of Life and Spirits. Hereby a Chriſtian (ſaith <hi>Bernard</hi>) is made more meek to be reproved, more patient to labour, more fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent to love, more ready to obey, and more Devout to give God thanks. In a word, your Heart by this feaſt of fat things, and refined Wines, will be more ſtrengthned to the practice of all Holy Virtues, to the maſtery of all Corruptions, and to the Conqueſt
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:63142:76"/>
of all Temptations, and ſupport to go on in its work and way, without ſinking under its burthen.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Beſides how could you think that you live well, if you ſhould live in the neglect or omiſſion of ſo great a Duty as this of Receiving the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, which was the Requeſt and Legacy of your dying Saviour, with ſtrict Command appendant and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>next thereunto, <hi>Do thus in Remembrance of me?</hi> Would not that be a living in Rebellion againſt his Law, a ſlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his Body and Blood, while you have a Command to Communicate therein? Unpreparedneſs may be your Sin, but cannot be a warrantable plea for abſtaining.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Now that you may ſo make your Addreſſes hereunto, as to come worthily, be careful of theſe four fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing particulars.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. To know and underſtand the Nature and Ends of this Feaſt.</item>
                  <item>2. To be ſuch a Perſon as the Maſter of the Feaſt would have his gueſts to be.</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="140" facs="tcp:63142:77"/>3. To make your ſelf ready be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you come to it.</item>
                  <item>4. To behave your ſelf ſo at it, as becomes a gueſt at that Royal Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXX.</hi> Of the Nature of the Sacrament of the Lords Supper.</head>
               <p>ENdeavour to get a right under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the Nature of this Divine Myſtery, ſo as to know what you feed on there. All People love to have light when they are at a Feaſt, to ſee what they eat. If you have not the light of knowledge, ſo as to ſee what you eat in the Lords Supper, which is the great Myſtery of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, you do not then diſcern the Lords Body, and ſo cannot be a worthy Receiver.</p>
               <p>Now as for the Nature of this Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sacrament, conſider both the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, and alſo the inſide of it.</p>
               <p>The outſide contains, 1. The Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramental
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:63142:77"/>
Elements, Bread and Wine 2. The Sacramental Rites or Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p>The Sacramental Elements are Bread and Wine, which being duly Conſecrated, are plain and viſible Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentations, and Divine Memori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als of the Body and Blood of Jeſus Chriſt: But yet they are not bare Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentations thereof, they are not meer ſhadowy Significations and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblances: For God doth not nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh and feed our Souls with thin and empty Shadows, weak and languiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Repreſentations, or naked Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blems: And therefore we muſt fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther look on them as real Pledges, and Seals or Inſtruments of Conveyance of Chriſt, and the fruits of his Death, in a Myſtical manner to the Faith of his People, which comes to paſs by Virtue of our Lords Inſtitution, whereupon he that duly receives the Elements, receives the thing ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by them, and vail'd therein. As among Men, a pledge confirms a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract, and a Seal conveys an Eſtate,
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:63142:78"/>
Houſe or Land, by Virtue of the Law of the Land: So by Virtue of Chriſts Inſtitution, the Covenant of grace is by the Sacramental Elements confirm'd betwixt God and the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Receiver, and Jeſus Chriſt, with all his benefits, truly exhibited and conveyed from God to the believing Communicant (though not as through a Conduit Pipe, as if they were Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally contained therein, yet) as an Eſtate is Conveyed from the Giver, by Wax and Seal, which is delivered by the Hand of his Meſſenger, or as the Poſſeſſion of a Houſe, is deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by a Key, and of Land, by a Sod or Turf. And ſo when Chriſt ſaith by the Miniſter, Take, This is my Body or my Blood, he doth as much as ſay, Take theſe, they are to thee my Body and Blood, <hi>i. e.</hi> real Pledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, together with which I give thee my ſelf, according as a Man in world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Matters, doth by Pledges give the thing ſignified thereby; as if he that's about giving poſſeſſion of a Houſe, ſhould give a Key, and ſay, Take it,
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:63142:78"/>
here is poſſeſſion of my Houſe, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livering an Evidence Sealed, ſhould ſay, Take this, here is my Land. And upon this account, the Cup is called by the Apoſtle, the Communion of the Blood of Chriſt, and the Bread broken the Communion of the Body of Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16. where the Apoſtle ſignifies to us, that the Eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Drinking of Believers in the Lords Supper, is a real Communicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in his Meritorious Death, and All-ſufficient Sacrifice, and a true Partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation of the Bleſſed Fruits of the Croſs. As among the <hi>Jews,</hi> thoſe that did eat of the Sacrifice, did partake of the Altar; <hi>ver.</hi> 18. that is, of the Sacrifice offered upon the Altar: So among Chriſtians, to Eat and Drink by Faith in the Lords Supper, is to be partaker of his Immaculate Sacrifice; once for all, offered up upon the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar of the Croſs. The Covenant is as the Deed, that intitles us to all the Riches of Grace, and Regions of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; but the Sacrament is the Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that doth Inveſt us therein.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="144" facs="tcp:63142:79"/>The Sacramental Actions or Rites, are on the Miniſters part, 1. The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration, by Bleſſing and giving thanks. 2. Breaking and Delivering. And then on the Communicants part, the Actions or Rites are, Taking, Eating, and Drinking.</p>
               <p>The inſide of the Sacrament, or the Spiritual thing Signified and Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched in the outward Sacrament; this is Chriſt himſelf, as offered up upon Mount <hi>Calvary,</hi> together with the precious Fruits of the Croſs, which bare better Fruits to us, than all the Trees of Paradiſe did; as Olives of Peace and Reconciliation with God, Cluſters of the Grapes of <hi>Canaan,</hi> Righteouſneſs and Grace, Joy and Gladneſs, Life and Salvation. The Elements of the Bread and Wine, ſignifie the Body and Blood of Chriſt, with the pretious Fruits thereof, and the breaking of the Bread, ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies the Crucifying or Sacrificing of Chriſt; And the Delivery of the Bread and Wine, Chriſts Delivering of himſelf with his Benefits. And the
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:63142:79"/>
Taking, Eating, and Drinking point forth the Communicants thankful accepting, and uſing that pretious gift. Here's the glory and divinity of the myſtery.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXI.</hi> Of the Ends of the Sacrament.</head>
               <p>ENdeavour to underſtand well the Ends of this Sacrament. Now for your more clear and diſtinct un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding hereof, I ſhall premiſe this one thing, <hi>viz.</hi> That this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lords Supper in the true notion of it, is a Feaſt, and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly a Feaſt upon a Sacrifice, or a Feaſt upon that which was once of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered up in Sacrifice to God, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Body and Blood of Chriſt, which are repreſented in the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Elements of Bread and Wine. And thus it is parallel unto, or bears proportion with, the Jewiſh Feaſts under the Law, which were made upon thoſe things, which they had
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:63142:80"/>
firſt offered up in Sacrifice to God: for it was an antient cuſtom among the Jews (as alſo generally among the Heathen) to link Feaſting and Sacrificing together, and to Eat of the things which themſelves had Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificed, and ſo had a Communion therein. This they did to ſignifie a Foederal or Covenanting Rite, and ſolemnity betwixt God and Them, as alſo a Covenanting League of friendſhip among themſelves, who did eat thereof. This being premi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, you may more plainly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the ends of this Sacrament, which are theſe following.</p>
               <p>The firſt end of this Sacrament is to be nouriſhment to our inward man, or that the Divine Nature in us might thrive, The end of a Feaſt is nouriſhment. This Sacred Feaſt was inſtituted to nouriſh and feed the Soul, to ſtrengthen and increaſe its Graces. Hence it's expreſt by Eating and Drinking, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.24, 25. Chriſt comes to the Soul as <hi>Melchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedeck</hi> to <hi>Abraham</hi> with Bread and
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:63142:80"/>
Wine. The very Body and Blood of Chriſt, which were a Sacrifice, as they were offered up to God, in that one full and ſufficient oblation upon the Croſs are Meat and Drink for the Souls nouriſhment as they are offered unto us, and ſet before us in the Diſhes of the outward Sacrament, and ſo Chriſt Crucified is truly and really, but Spiritually and Myſtically given to us in the Lords Supper to be our Nutriment, as he was given for us in the Sacrifice and Oblation upon the Croſs, to be our propitiation and atonement: Chriſts Fleſh is Meat indeed, and his Blood Drink indeed, and do become one with us ſpiritual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for our nouriſhment, as our Bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Meat and Drink do, being turn'd into our ſubſtance, here there is a kind of Divine Coalition into the ſame Nature: hence our Saviour ſaid, He that eateth me ſhall live by me, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.57. It's ſtoried of <hi>Arte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſia</hi> that ſhe ſo dearly loved her Husband <hi>Mauſolus,</hi> that after he was dead, ſhe took the Aſhes of his Urn,
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:63142:81"/>
and mingled them with her Drink, and ſo intomb'd her dead Husband in her living body. A faithful Soul that is eſpouſed to Chriſt, doth this at the Sacrament, Eating and Drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there of her crucified Saviour by a Spiritual Commeſſation, thus ſhe lives by him, and hath him as it were intomb'd in her Heart.</p>
               <p>Therefore whenſoever you come to this Heavenly Banquet, come with this end that your Soul may receive increaſe and nouriſhment in Grace thereby, that you may have Chriſt become one with you, as your food doth whereby you thrive and grow. But yet you muſt not think to get any nouriſhment, from the out-ſide of the Sacrament, from the outward Rynd or Bark, or Skin of the Ordinance, or by feeding on the outward Elements, if you reſt there. This would be to ſcrape or lick the Diſh only, or out-ſide of the Cup, to play with the Trencher and let the Meat alone, and to go
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:63142:81"/>
away whole and untoucht from the Table.</p>
               <p>The ſecond end for which this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament was inſtituted, is a ſolemn Commemoration of Chriſt and him Crucified, or the celebrating a memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial of him in the Church thr<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ughout all Ages. Publick Feaſts were uſually made for the perſerving the memory of ſome great Benefactor. Now this Sacrament of the Paſſion is a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Feaſt for the whole Church of God in all Ages; and was it not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted for to keep a perpetual me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of the Founder of it, our dear Lord and infinite Benefactor? This will appear by his own words at the firſt Inſtitution, do this in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of me, <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.19. <hi>i. e.</hi> of me as Crucified and Dying, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> expreſly interprets it, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.16. For as oft as ye do eat this Bread, and Drink this Cup, ye do ſhew forth the Lords Death till he come; and therefore it was purpoſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ordain'd for the retaining a more ſpecial Memory of his Death and
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:63142:82"/>
Paſſion. For the Sacrament (as I premiſed) was a feaſt upon a Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and ſo it was ordain'd by Chriſt more particularly and ſpecially, to commemorate that oblation of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf upon the Croſs for the Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the World, till he come to Judgment, to eternize the memory of his great and infinite love and goodneſs in dying for us, and to tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit it to all ſucceeding Ages and Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations. The Lord hath, ſo done this marvellous work, that it ought to be had in everlaſting remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance.</p>
               <p>Therefore in all your addreſſes to this Sacrament of the Paſſion, come for this end, to keep in a thankful and affectionate memory the great and infinite ſufferings of Chriſt for our Sins. Remember his Death and Paſſion through the whole Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Action, and that with the moſt enlarged and enraviſht affections and meltings of Heart, and the immortal hatred of thoſe ſins that put him up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on dying for us, and the ſhedding of
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:63142:82"/>
His moſt precious blood, one drop whereof is of more value than a Mountain of Pearl as big as the whole Earth.</p>
               <p>The third End of the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per is a ſolemn renewing of the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſmal Covenant. The Feaſts anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently made upon Sacrifices were ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally uſed (as I obſerved before) to ſignifie thereby a Covenanting with God. Therefore this Supper of the Lord being in the true notion of it (as I ſaid) a feaſt upon the bloody Sacrifice offered by Chriſt upon the Croſs for us, it doth clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inſinuate to us, that it was appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be a mutual ſtipulation or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venanting betwixt God and his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municants, hence Chriſt ſaid con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Cup, This is the New Teſtament or Covenant in my Blood<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>i. e.</hi> the Rite or Solemnity of the, New Covenant (to declare and ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie the conſent of parties thereunto, and reſolution to perform the duties of it) inſinuating thereby, that as the Legal Sacrifices on which the
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:63142:83"/>
People did eat were as Rites of an old ſuperannuated Covenant, ſo was this Sacrament a Rite of a New Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, by uſing whereof we do teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie our engagements to perform it, as God doth his for making us par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of all the Bleſſings couched in it. So that this Sacrament on Gods part doth ſignifie a ſolemn de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livery of Jeſus Chriſt, his pretious Body and Blood, together with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſins (for which that bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Body was broken and torn, and that Blood ſpilt) and all other fruits of his Death. And on our part it ſignifies a free acceptance thereof, and a hearty delivery of our ſelves up to the intire obedience of him, as we ingaged in the New Covenant to do: ſo that conſequently one great End of this Sacrament is to be a pledge of our happy participation of the Body and Blood of Chriſt, with remiſſion of Sins, Juſtification, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption and Title to the Regions of Bliſs, and all other the ineſtimable benefits thereof. Hence it's called
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:63142:83"/>
the Communion of the Body and Blood of Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16. where the Apoſtle doth plainly declare than the Sacramental Bread and Cup are aſſured pledges of our Communion with the Body and Blood of Chriſt, <hi>i. e.</hi> of the Communication thereof to us if duely received.</p>
               <p>Therefore in all your Addreſſes to the Lords Table, go with this <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cope and End, that you may have a part and portion in Chriſts Body and Blood, remiſſion of ſins, and recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation thereby, with all other me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of the Blood of the Croſs, which God hath Covenanted to make over to you. And go alſo with this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, that you may renew the ingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and declare that you will ſtand to the terms of the Baptiſmal Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, that you will keep firm and conſtant to that holy League, and ſtand out in a holy War againſt all the Enemies of Chriſt, and never revolt or go to the Enemies quarters; but as a faithful confederate with him, will alway fight under his Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:63142:84"/>
againſt the World, the Fleſh and the Devil, and continue to be on Chriſts ſide, or of his Religion to your lifes end.</p>
               <p>The fourth End of this Sacrament is to be a pledge and improvement of that love, unity and concord that ought to be among Chriſtians. Thoſe that did feaſt upon the Sacrifices an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently (as I before hinted) did uſe to enter into a Covenant of friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip among themſelves as well as betwixt God and Them. And it hath been an univerſal cuſtom, throughout the World to make Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venants or Leagues of Friendſhip by Eating and Drinking together. This bleſſed Supper of the Lord is really and truly a publick Love-feaſt, and was deſigned by our Saviour for this end, the promoting Love and Union among all his People, and to ſhew that they ſhould all cleave together in one Spirit, as they have all been partakers of one Bread, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.17. If then it was a Love-feaſt and the feaſt ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main, let not the love be excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="chapter">
               <pb n="155" facs="tcp:63142:84"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXII.</hi> Of Habitual Qualifications of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municants.</head>
               <p>BEfore you make Addreſſes to this Heavenly Banquet, ſee that you be habitually ſuch a perſon as the Maſter of the Feaſt our Lord Jeſus Chriſt would have his gueſts to be. Therefore you muſt ſet ſome porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of time apart, before the Feaſt Day, to examin your ſelf, whether you be ſuch a perſon or no, <hi>i. e.</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you be a Real and Serious Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, one that is truly, and in good earneſt Godly. When the King ſaw one amongſt his Gueſts, that had not on a Wedding Garment, that was not Veſted with the Robes of Chriſts Righteouſneſs for Juſtification, nor of Inherent Righteouſneſs for Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, he commanded to take him, and bind him Hand and Foot, and to caſt him into utter Darkneſs, <hi>Math.</hi> 22.13. The Wrath of God will be
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:63142:85"/>
up againſt ſuch unworthy Gueſts, as the King's was againſt <hi>Haman,</hi> at the Banquet of Wine, and will give Sentence againſt them accordingly. The <hi>Indians,</hi> when they firſt came into theſe <hi>Northern</hi> Countreys, thought Roſes had been Fire. Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Roſe of <hi>Sharon</hi> will be real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a Conſuming Fire, a devouring Flame to unworthy Communicants. He that Eats and Drinks unworthily, Eats and Drinks his own Damnation, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.29. it's as if the Apoſtle ſhould ſay, he ſwallows Damnation; and this is more th<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n to ſwallow down Flames here in the World. It would be well for ſuch, if this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament proved only an empty Feaſt to them, but it proves mortal Poyſon, and like Poyſon taken in Wine, works with the fierceſt Violence. If you be an unworthy Gueſt at the Lords Table, you will be guilty of the Body and blood of the Lord, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.27. your Soul will be die<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pred in Blood. I mention not this to diſhearten you from going to that
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:63142:85"/>
Bleſſed Feaſt (for you ought to go) but to perſuade you to go as a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Gueſt, that your going may be for your Everlaſting Comfort, and not for your Confuſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXIII.</hi> Of Actual Qualifications.</head>
               <p>MAke your ſelf actually ready to come to this great Solemnity, this Holy Sacrament of the Lords Supper. It's not enough that you be habitually, unleſe you be actually pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared. If you were invited to a Feaſt by ſome great Perſon, you would not ſatisfie your ſelf to go in your ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Dreſs, though it were neat and handſom, but you would put your ſelf to ſome more than ordinary pains to ſpruce and trim up your ſelf, ſo as not to have a Hair amiſs. And ought you not to be more careful to Beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie, Deck and Trim up your Soul afreſh, by Special and more than Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Devotions and Actions of Piety,
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:63142:86"/>
before you come to this High and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtick Solemnity, this Tremendous Myſtery? as <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> calls it. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Meat, it's good to uſe ſome Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe (as Phyſicians ſay) to ſtir up the Natural Heat, for to promote Digeſtion: And ſo before this Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Feaſt, it's good to Exerciſe our Souls, for the ſtirring up our Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Appetite thereunto, for the warm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, heating and quickning of all thoſe Graces and Affections that are neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for a worthy Communicant, which are, Faith, Repentance, Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gring Deſires, Love to God and our Neighbour, Joy, Thankfulneſs, and Reſolutions of New Obedience. You muſt not only have the habit of theſe Graces, but they muſt be made rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, new ſcoured and prepared, ſo as they may work more kindly at the Sacrament; there muſt be a tuning of the Viol, and a winding up of the Strings, the ſeveral Faculties of the Soul. Now you muſt rally up all your Affections, all the Forces of your Soul, and get them all in a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:63142:86"/>
Frame, and due Poſture, for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſing themſelves at this Sacred So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity. You muſt premeditate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you go, of all the work that you are to do at the Sacrament, and ſo thereby fit your ſelf for the better doing of it, when you come there.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXIV.</hi> Of Suitable Behaviour at the Table of the Lord.</head>
               <p>BE careful ſo to behave your ſelf at this Divine Feaſt, as becomes one of the Lords Gueſts. It's not ſufficient to get your Heart into a Devout Frame, before you Approach to this Table of the Lord, but it is requiſite alſo, that it be kept up in a Holy Tune, in a right Diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and ſuitable Deportment, during the whole Solemnity. It's not enough to Trim up ones ſelf to go to the Table of ſome Noble Perſon, but there muſt be alſo a becoming Beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour there, leſt Offence be given, by
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:63142:87"/>
any undecencies. And therefore that your Demeanour here may be proper and becoming, I ſhall inſtruct you how, and in what particular Seaſons or Paſſages of the Adminiſtration, your Sacramental Graces reſpectively are to be exerciſed. I hinted to you in the former Chapter, which are thoſe Graces that are moſt proper to be exerciſed at the Sacrament, and ſhall now ſhew you in what Order and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, and in what ſeaſon they are apt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and pertinently to be acted there.</p>
               <p>When you are called up by the Miniſter to draw near to the Table of Bleſſing, think you hear Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf by his Miniſter calling you up, and bidding you welcom. And then Exerciſe Humble Thankfulneſs and Joy, together with hungring deſires, and let your Heart ſay: Lord, what am I, that thou ſhouldſt ſo far condeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend, as to invite me a poor Worm, thy worthleſs Hand-maid to thy Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Table? And to admit ſuch a wretched Creature to the Banquet of Spiced Wine, who have deſerved
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:63142:87"/>
nothing but Gall and Vinegar to Drink? My Soul therefore doth Magnifie the Lord, and my Spirit rejoyceth in God my Saviour, for he hath regarded the Lowlineſs of his Hand-Maid, from henceforth all the powers of my Soul ſhall call thee Bleſſed. Lord haſt thou now called me into thy Banquetting-Houſe? I do promiſe here, that while the King ſitteth at the Table (and I there with him) my Spicknard ſhall ſend forth the ſmell thereof. My Faith, Deſires, Love and Thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: Yea, all my Graces ſhall ſend forth a ſweet and holy Perfure to pleaſe him. O that the ſame Love that hath prepared a Table for me, and now called me to it, would prepare me for it, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh my Soul with Love and Sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs there!</p>
               <p>At the Miniſters reciting the words of Inſtitution, Separating and Bleſſing of the Bread and Wine, whereby they are Conſecrated; Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe Faith and Thankfulneſs, and
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:63142:88"/>
fervent Deſires to God the Father, and ſay, Lord, out of thine infinite Love, thou didſt ſeparate and ſet apart the Lord Jeſus from all Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and appointed him for our Redeemer, and didſt bleſs him with the Spirit above meaſure, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king him the rich Treaſury, and common Stock of Grace, a Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain over-flowing, to the ſupply of all Believers: Let him not be to me a lockt Treaſure, or a Fountain Sealed up, but Bleſs and Sanctifie theſe Creatures of Bread and Wine to me, that they may be the Body and Blood of Chriſt in effect to me, for my Attonement, Peace and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitiation, and pardon of all my Sins, and convey Spiritual Life, Nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Comfort to me abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. O let my Soul be ſteept in ſweetneſs; and let the Rock pour out Oyl into me, even the Oyl of Grace, and of Joy and Gladneſs alſo.</p>
               <p>When you look upon the Bread and Wine after Conſecration, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:63142:88"/>
Faith to diſcern the Lords Body; and look now upon them not as common Bread and Wine, but as Sacramental Repreſentations, Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually Exhibiting the Body and Blood of Chriſt, look by Faith be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond theſe outward Elements and ſay; Lord, thou doſt here ſend me a covered Diſh of Royal Cheer from Heaven, from thine own Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, as to a Beloved Friend, or Dear Child: Teach me to take off the outward Cover, and to ſee plainly and clearly the rare Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates that are laid in it. Let me ſo imploy my outward Senſes, in minding the out-ſide of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſo as to raiſe my Spiritual Senſes, to ſee and diſcern the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide thereof, and the Glorious Myſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries couched in it. And here ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe further longing deſires after thoſe vailed Myſteries, and ſay, As the Heart pants after the Water-Brooks, ſo panteth my Soul after thee O God, my Soul is athirſt for God, yea, even for the Living God.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="164" facs="tcp:63142:89"/>When you ſee the Bread broken and the Wine poured out, then you ſee the lively Spectacle of a Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Saviour. Let then Repentance be renewed, Faith, Love and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions, for New Obedience, and Holy Deſires alſo Acted and Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated in the Soul. Repreſent now to your ſelf in this Myſtery, what our Lord Jeſus endured when he hung upon his painful Bed of Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows the Croſs, and ſay to your ſelf, canſt thou look upon a bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Saviour, without a broken Heart? upon a bleeding Chriſt, without a bleeding Soul? Upon a pierced Jeſus, without a Heart pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced thorow with Godly ſorrow, for thy Sins that pierced him? Doth not every Orifice made by the Nayls, the Thorns, and the Spear in that pretious tormented and pained Body, and every drop of Blood that iſſued thence, call aloud to thee for Repentance of thoſe Sins that cauſed theſe Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments? I do therefore here Vow
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:63142:89"/>
and Covenant to take a revenge up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my Sins, and give them their mortal wound, and cauſe them to Bleed to Death, uſing them, as they uſed my Dear Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour. O what Streams of match<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Love were theſe, that flowed from a Dying Saviour, laying down his Life for me; and do not theſe call for ſtreamings of Love back again from my Breaſt towards him? O that my Soul may be ſprinkled with that Blood, which iſſued from that Fountain of infinite Love! O that it may be Bathed in that Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Bath, ſet open for Sin and for Uncleanneſs! Whom have I in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven but thee, and there's none up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Earth that I can deſire beſides thee, my bleeding Saviour.</p>
               <p>When the Miniſter comes and delivers to you the Bread or Wine, look on him as doing it in Chriſts Name, and here ſtir up Faith and Love to God. Think with admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Love, how God in Chriſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livers up himſelf in Covenant to
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:63142:90"/>
you, offering to be your God, your Reconciled Father and Redeemer: And believe with Joy and Thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, that you hear Chriſt by the Miniſter ſaying to your Faith, Take my Body and Blood, all the Riches of that Covenant, which was Sealed with my Blood, all the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings coucht in that Bleſſed Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>When you take theſe at the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters hands, then let the Hand of Faith ſtretch forth it ſelf, to reach God, and ſtir up your ſelf to take hold on him, and put forth intire Reſolutions of New Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and ſay, Lord, by taking this, I do Covenant with thee, that I take thee with my whole Heart, to be my Lord, to be ruled and governed as well as ſaved by thee, and I do here ſeriouſly devote my ſelf, both Body and Soul to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire Obedience of thee.</p>
               <p>When you are eating the Bread, then lift up your Heart by Faith to God and ſay; I believe, Lord,
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:63142:90"/>
that thy fleſh is meat indeed; thou that didſt Dye for me, art the Bread of Life, that ſhall nouriſh my Soul to eternal Life. My Soul ſhall be ſatisfied as with marrow and fatneſs, and my Mouth ſhall praiſe thee with joyful Lips. And here by eating this Bread, I do Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with thee, to be thy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant and Obedient Child for ever.</p>
               <p>And when you are drinking of the Wine, or immediately upon it, ſay, Lord, thy Blood is Drink in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed. O that my Soul may taſt the refreſhings of this Heavenly Wine! O ſtay me with Flagons, Comfort me with thy Love, which is better than Wine. I believe that thy Blood was ſhed for the Remiſſion of Sins, O that I may be waſht from all mine in that Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Laver! And that I may hear the ſoft Voice of thy Spirit whiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pering to my Soul, Daughter be of good Cheer, thy Sins be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given thee. Bleſs the Lord, O my Soul, and that is within me bleſs
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:63142:91"/>
his Holy Name, who forgiveth all thine Iniquities, and healeth all thy Diſeaſes.</p>
               <p>When you look upon the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municants receiving with you, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe Love to the Saints, and ſay, where the Carcaſs is, where the Crucified Body of my Saviour is, thither will the believing Eagles be gathered together, and ſhall not I be joyned in love with all that Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Flock, and Holy Society? Theſe Eagles do all feed on Blood, the Blood of a Crucified Chriſt, and hath not this a Cementing Virtue to unite Affections? Theſe are the Friends of the Bride groom, and ſhall not I make them my Friends? Shall not the Beloved of my Saviour, be the Beloved Ones of my Soul?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="chapter">
               <pb n="169" facs="tcp:63142:91"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXV.</hi> What is to be done after the Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration is ended.</head>
               <p>VVHEN the ſolemnity is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; go home with a glad heart, and a chearful Spirit, and ſay to your ſelf: what, did <hi>Haman</hi> go from <hi>Eſthers</hi> Banquet of Wine, with a glad Heart, glorying in the honour of his being there? And ſhall not I much more rejoyce and glory, who have been in the Spouſes banqueting Houſe, where his Banner over me was love; and have been royally entertain'd by the King of Saints with the choiceſt delicates of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven!</p>
               <p>When you are come home re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire your ſelf into privacy for a little time, and ask your ſelf what your demeanour was at the Lords Table, and what happy fruit you have found of your being there. What melt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, or ſoftnings of Heart? What
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:63142:92"/>
glimpſes of Love? What cheriſhing Beams of the Spirit? What ſtrength, vigor and livelineſs of Soul? What ſecret ſpringings and elevations of Spirit? What ſpiritual quicknings and refreſhings have you had at that Feaſt of Fat Things and refined Wines? And according as you find it with your Heart upon this ſhort tryal, ſo do you anſwerably make your addreſſes unto God. If you have found the efficacy of the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, and ſweet ſatisfaction there, bleſs God for it, and ſing glory to God in the higheſt, and pray earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to him, that it may abide upon your Soul, but if you find no Divine reliſhes, no drops of ſweetneſs, but are come away with an earthy and droſſy Soul, then humble your ſelf before God, and labour to find out the Sin that was the obſtruction, and remove it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Be watchful afterwards, leſt the World or any trifling occaſions damp thoſe influences, which you found at the Sacrament. All per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:63142:92"/>
are moſt careful of themſelves after they come out of a hot Bath, leſt they ſhouid take cold. When you have been at this Spiritual Bath of the Sacrament, be exceeding care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful that cold get not info the Heart, that thoſe affections that were warm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and heated there, be not cooled again. Let not thoſe ſweet gales of Devotion, that did blow within you, at the Lords Table, be preſently driven away with a counterblaſt from Satan or the World. Satan will now be moſt ready to Way-lay you, for to rob you of your Jewels, theſe pretious Love-tokens of Peace, and Joy, and holy Vigour, which you received from your bleſſed Lord at his Table, and therefore you have more need after you have been there to look well about you, and to walk more circumſpectly, and to live more orderly. A diſorderly Diet after Phyſick received will do more hurt than before. Live ever after as one that hath been at the Table of the Lord, then ſhall you at the
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:63142:93"/>
end of your life be welcomed to the Supper of the Lamb, in the kingdom of Glory, and the Cloath never drawn to all Eternity.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>The Concluſion.</head>
               <p>I Have now drawn out to you the Lineaments of practical Religion (the chief Lines and Features of Godlineſs) which conſiſts mainly in believing in, and devoting your ſelf to God the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, in living by Faith, in holineſs of Heart and Life, in Love to God, in walking before God and in uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal obedience to him, ſtrictly and circumſpectly, as alſo in Mortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Repentance, praiſing of God and delighting in him, Humility, Meekneſs, Love and Charity, exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſing Grace in all Conditions and Relations, well ſpending of your time, eſpecially on the Lords day, and waiting upon God in the Holy Ordinances of Prayer, Word and Sacraments. It's now your duty not
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:63142:93"/>
only to view theſe lines, but to draw out the ſame in your practice, and to mould your ſelf into the like form. I have endeavoured to anoint your right ear with wholeſome advice, ſee that it be your care to get your right foot anointed with the Oil of Grace, that you may ſmoothly and chearfully walk in the way here Chaulkt out before you, till you come to the Land of Glory.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:63142:94"/>
            <head>Books Printed for, and are to be ſold by <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt,</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Three Crowns</hi> in <hi>Cheapſide,</hi> near <hi>Mercers</hi> Chapel.</head>
            <p>A Body of practical Divinity con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of above 176 Sermons on the leſſer Catechiſm compoſed by the Reverend Aſſembly of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> with a Supple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſome Sermons on ſeveral Texts of Scripture, by <hi>Tho. Watſon</hi> formerly Miniſter of St. <hi>Stephens Walbrook</hi> Printed from his own hand writing, recommended by ſeveral Miniſters to Maſters of Families and others.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Synodicon in Gallia Reformata,</hi> or the Acts, Decrees, Deciſions, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons of the Reformed Churches in <hi>France.</hi> Being 1. A moſt faithful and impartial Hiſtory of the riſe,
<pb facs="tcp:63142:94"/>
growth perfection and decay of the Reformation in that Kingdom, with its fatal Cataſtrophe upon the revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the Edict at <hi>Nants</hi> in the year 1685. 2. The Confeſſion of Faith &amp; Diſcipline of thoſe Churches. 3. A Collection of Speeches, Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Sacred Politicks, Caſes of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and Controverſies in Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity determined and reſolved by thoſe Grave Aſſemblies. 4. Many excellent expedients for preventing and healing Schiſms in the Churches and for re-uniting the diſmembred body of divided Proteſtants. 5. The Laws, Government and Maintenance of the Colledges, Univerſities, and Miniſters, together, with their Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of Diſcipline upon delinquent Miniſters and Church Members. 6 A Record of very many illuſtrious Events of Divine Providence relat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to thoſe Churches. The whole col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected and compoſed out of the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Manuſcript Acts of thoſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Synods, a work never be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore extant in any Language, in two
<pb facs="tcp:63142:95"/>
Vol. by <hi>John Quick</hi> &amp;c. Fol.</p>
            <p>The Sure Mercies of David: Or, a Second Part of Heart-treaſure. Wherein is contained the ſum and ſubſtance of Goſpel-mercies purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by Chriſt, and Promiſed in the Covenant of Grace, together with the ſeveral ways how they are made ſure to all the Heirs of Promiſe, and how they are to be improved for the Saints Fort and Defence, Settlement and Incouragement in ſhaking and back-ſliding times. By <hi>O. Heywood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Cloſet-prayer a Chriſtian Duty: or, a Treatiſe upon <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.6. By <hi>O. Heywood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Baptiſmal Bonds renewed. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome Meditations upon <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.5. By <hi>O. H.</hi> M. A.</p>
            <p>Meetneſs for Heaven promoted in ſome brief Meditations upon <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 1.12. Diſcovering the nature and neceſſity of habitual and actual Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for Heaven here, in all that hope for Heaven hereafter. By <hi>O. H.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Epiſtolary Diſcourſe on the great aſſiſtances to a Chriſtians Faith,
<pb facs="tcp:63142:95"/>
and for a more Intire Reſt and Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance in the higheſt Trials and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventures thereof. With a Second Part, upon the Preſent Times, and theſe rare Viciſſitudes of Providence in the Publick State of <hi>Britain</hi> in this Age. To which an Appendix is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the Cloſe. By <hi>R. Fleming.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Diſcourſe of Earthquakes; as they are Supernatural and Premoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory Signs to a Nation; with a reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to what hath occurred in this Year 1692. And ſome ſpecial Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections thereon. As alſo on that Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity and Aſſurance of Mind, which is attainable in the Light and Power of Religion, under the greateſt Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizals and Terrors of Senſe. With ſome Enquiry upon the Grounds, both of our Fears and Hopes, as to the publick State of the Church of Chriſt in this Day. By the Author of the Fulfilling of the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>The Confirming Work of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Or its Great Things made plain, by their Primary Evidences and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations. Whereby the meaneſt
<pb facs="tcp:63142:96"/>
in the Church, may ſoon be made able to render a Rational account of their Faith Written by <hi>R. Fleming,</hi> Author of the Fulfilling of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
            <p>A Defence of Mr. <hi>M.</hi> H's Brief Enquiry into the Nature of Schiſm, and the vindication of it. With Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections upon a Pamphlet called the Review, &amp;c. And a Brief Hiſtorical Account of Nonconformity, from the Reformation to this Preſent Time.</p>
            <p>England's Alarum: Being an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of God's moſt Conſiderable Diſpenſations of Mercy and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment towards theſe Kingdoms for Fourteen Years laſt paſt. And alſo, of the ſeveral ſorts of Sins and Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners therein; Eſpecially the Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murers againſt the Preſent Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. With an Earneſt Call to ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Humiliation, Supplication and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, as the Chief Means of Proſpering their Majeſties Counſels and Preparations. Dedicated to the King and Queen.</p>
            <p>A Sermon Preached at the Funeral
<pb facs="tcp:63142:96"/>
of the Reverend Mr. <hi>Thomas Shewell,</hi> Maſter of Arts, and Miniſter of the Goſpel in <hi>Coventry.</hi> Who went up well into the Pulpit, <hi>Jan.</hi> 15. and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Prayed, and Named the Text, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.12. was ſeized by an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexy, and dyed within a few Hours. By <hi>William Tongue,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
